Thank you.
This is an easy one.
I'll make a lot of small ones.
I'll make a little bigger.
I'll make some small ones.
I'll make a lot of small ones.
I want some small ones.
I'll make a lot more small ones.
I'll make some small ones.
Ok, so I can't do this.
Thank you.
so
b
Okay.
OK, so let's go.
Nose and the other ones, we have a nice restaurant, and we have to make this place for another restaurant, and we are going to decorate the restaurant.
I like the bread.
I'm good.
First, we close the door and then we can start.
Welcome back to CSE 435 distributed systems one as you might have seen from the lecture
recording I hope.
I am your professor.
Good to see you in person ok.
I am back and for the rest of the quarter we will meet in person especially for the
in person sections and then for the flex you get to choose if you want to come in person
or not.
at any moment in time.
So what I want to do today is,
I wanna talk a little bit about announcements,
then I'll leave some room for Q and A
if you have any questions regarding the syllabus,
class structure, programming assignment one,
quizzes as well, okay?
And then what I want to do is,
I wanna spend some time over the instructions
on how to access your GitLab repository.
There's a few things that are very, let's say, awkward,
there's some additional setup that we have to do,
and I'll explain why we need to do it.
And it has more to do with the fact that we're using
universal resources and they have some policies
about react as those resources,
which complicates things a little bit.
Okay? And then afterwards,
we'll continue talking about distributed systems.
I think my plan is to finish
talking about Chapter 1
this week, and then next week,
we'll talk about Programming Assignment 2,
and then Chapter 2. Okay?
So, first things first, announcements.
So, I ended up releasing
quiz number one today. So as mentioned in the syllabus you have an interval of time
where you can attempt the quizzes. So the quizzes will be nine quizzes in total,
one extra credit, one in the last week and then eight quizzes throughout the rest of the quarter.
So quiz number one was released you have until Monday next week, so September 21st
at midnight, to attempt to take the quiz. Once you attempt to take the quiz you will have 10 minutes to complete.
The quiz will basically be for multiple choice questions
with only one correct answer.
The quiz is open book, open note, open internet.
So you can take it whenever you want,
so this applies for all sections in this class.
The quiz will cover chapter one of the course book
until and excluding the security goal of distributed system.
So basically it's what I covered in the lecture recording
from last week from Wednesday.
So the way I would recommend that you prepare
for the quiz is by reading chapter 1, so it will be half of chapter 1. It will take you
about 1 to 2 hours to go over it. So it's not really that long. Okay. Or we can re-watch
the lecture, you know, and then go and attempt the quiz. Once you're done completing the
quiz, you'll get your score and then after the deadline, I will also release so the D2L
is set up to release automatically the questions and also the correct answer. So you'll be
to check them. Okay, in terms of other announcements, so the deadline for
programming assignment 1 has been extended because the GitLab accounts on
the GitLab server that is set up for this class were not ready yet, so I moved
the deadline by another week because I think I completed creating all of the
accounts yesterday and yesterday you should have received an email.
The repositories were also created yesterday as well.
So the deadline has been moved to Tuesday, September 29th.
So we have an additional week to complete this assignment.
Okay.
And then, as I mentioned regarding how do you access your repository,
I have some additional instructions here that were posted on D2L.
This is what we will follow today.
But before that, I want to make sure that I answer all of your questions first.
So if you have any questions regarding the syllabus, quiz, programming assignments,
anything else.
Yes.
Just the readings, are they mapped to each week?
So week one is chapter one, that kind of thing?
Or is it like one, two, and three of chapters before week one?
No.
So usually the quizzes will cover the concepts that were presented the week before.
So usually the first two or three weeks will be chapter one.
It just depends on how fast we move, and then chapter two for another two weeks, chapter
three for another two weeks.
and then we will stay on chapter I think four will be longer and I think that's
where it ends there's also a chapter five but chapter five you won't have
questions in the quiz you will only have some questions in the final exam but I'll
announce it so you will be able to see on D2L which chapters are actually being
covered or how far each chapter yes it was about where they were posted the
readings the readings yeah it's over here yeah so in the
announcement itself, I usually mention the quiz covers, for example here, chapter
one of the course book until and excluding security goal of the student systems. So I'll write for each of the quiz what it covers.
Any other questions? Well, I've got a few questions for you. So have you started
working on programming assignment one? So let's say if you've completed 10% of it,
you know, you just, you know, went on and maybe installed a hypervisor on your
computer you know if you started doing that you know raise your hand okay okay
that's fine you still have two weeks to complete you know my recommendation is
that you start ahead of time you know in case you encounter any kind of
difficulties the way you can reach out to me is again through office hours and
through email I'll promise that I'll try to reply in 24 hours to your email so
that's why the more ahead of time you start the better is also for me as well
to so that I can reply one time and then again to schedule office hours okay just
send me an email if you can 24 hours before
with the slot that you would prefer.
And keep in mind that the office hours are in hybrid
format. So you can decide if you want
to come in person or over Zoom.
I'm fine either way. And it doesn't matter
which section you are.
Okay? Alright. Very good.
Any other questions regarding the class structure?
Well, yes.
Since assignment one was extended
I just want to make sure I stay on top of it. When will
assignment two be due?
So it will be released next week.
and it will overlap by one week, but the deadline will be after Programming Assignment 1.
So usually you will see I think the assignments will overlap by a week I think,
between each other but they are related to each other.
So as you are completing Programming Assignment 2,
this will help you complete Programming Assignment 3 and so on and so forth.
In this class what we will attempt to do is to build a more complex application
to kind of simulate what would it take to bring, let's say, a single-core monolithic application
and transform it into a distributed application.
We will try to pay attention to the design goals.
So what I mentioned in the lecture recording as well,
there are some goals that people follow when they build distributed systems,
sharing of resources.
We want to build distributed systems because we want to share resources.
We have a bunch of computers and we want to be able to combine the computational and data resources that we have available over all of them.
We want to be able to achieve distribution transparency where basically we have a bunch of computers.
If you remember the definition from the first lecture, we said that a distributed system is a collection of independent computers
that appear to each user one single coherent system, right?
So distribution transparency will refer to that ability
to hide away the complexity of the system
and expose to the user a single uniform interface that they can access.
So you'll have to do the exact same thing.
So you'll provide one single interface,
but underneath the hood, right, your system will change and it will evolve
and it will become more and more distributed.
And then of course we will also take a look at size skin ability as well which we haven't
covered yet so this is one of the design goals that we'll talk about as well.
And then openness of course right so an important aspect is we want the distributed system or
the application that you are building, we want it to be easy to maintain, easy to extend
and easy to interoperate with other applications.
So throughout the assignments you will start with a very simple program and depending on
how well you've designed the software implementation of your program,
it will be either easier or harder for you to extend.
But this would be a good training exercise to learn what it takes
to actually build a more complex application.
Okay? Very good.
Any other questions?
Well, if at any point you remember a question,
even if it's about the syllabus or the class structure,
feel free to interrupt me at any moment.
I'd be more than happy to explain things, okay?
otherwise what I want to do
is I want to go over these
instructions on how to
access your repository
okay so
I'm going to go ahead and sit down for this one
so I can do some things on the
computer and you can follow
along with me
Alright
I think I pressed something here
I think this will disappear now.
Okay, very good.
So before we jump into the instructions,
I want to draw a quick diagram
on how this whole GitLab server works
and how your code will be copied
from one machine to the other.
So again, Git, I've included in D2L some resources.
So if you've never used Git before,
my recommendation is that you go over those resources.
If you have used it before, it's still useful to go over those resources.
You might learn some new things.
But the most important aspect is that this is what people use in the industry.
It's one of the tools that is used for software development,
including for the development of distributed applications as well.
So Git is a version control system.
It allows you to keep track of all of the modifications in your code.
And this is what we will be using in this class to actually upload, let's say, the assignment.
So instead of uploading the code on D2L or on a separate machine, I'd like you to actually use Git to upload it to an external repository.
So that repository will be hosted on the new form at cdm.de paul.de machine.
This is a machine that I set up, that I manage, and it's hosted using the DePaul infrastructure.
And because it's hosted by the DePaul infrastructure, they have a few rules on how do you access
this machine whenever you are using the SSH protocol.
The SSH stands for secure shell, and it's basically the mechanism that you will be using
to connect to that machine.
Now, you will not SSH to that machine.
All that you will be doing is you will be running the Git commands to clone your repository
and to push code to the repository on that machine.
And my recommendation is that you do that by using the SSH protocol.
with Git. Now, because of DePaul policies, whenever we're accessing the machine at DePaul
through SSH, we actually have to go through a bastion host or an SSH jump host, they call it.
So this is just an additional machine. You can consider it to be a proxy machine through which
all of the SSH connections have to go through. So let's say these instructions here are meant to
we're going to show you how do you set up this JamPost connection in a way where it will work in a seamless way so that you don't have to insert passwords, too many passwords, or you don't have to authenticate too many times whenever you have to do any kind of push command or pull command or clone command.
So, let me go ahead and open the whiteboard here so I can draw a little bit a diagram
so we can understand a little bit how your computer connects to the Neutron server and
where the Bastion host resides.
So let's say that, you know, this is the server.
So this is the Neutron server that is running a GitLab server instance.
And this is where you will have your repository.
Now GitLab calls them projects.
They mean the same thing.
It's basically the collection of source files and documentation that belongs to one of your projects.
And let's say that this is your personal computer.
I'm going to assume that you have a laptop or you can have a desktop computer as well.
So okay, it doesn't really matter.
If you were to use GitHub, the actual GitLab server, hosted by the company that created GitLab,
the way you would, let's say, work on your project is you would initiate a clone request
directly from your computer to the machine.
So you do Git clone.
And this will transfer the code to your machine.
And then you can write the code in your machine.
and then you can use the git push commands to synchronize your code with the other machine.
Now, if somebody else works on this code as well,
you can git pull commands to pull modifications back to your machine.
So, the most common commands that you will be using are the git clone for this class,
git pull if you have multiple machines that you're working from,
the git add command that allows you to tell git that you can keep track of these files,
they have been modified or updated, commit whenever you want to do a push, so you're
creating a transaction and then the push itself would actually move the
transactions to the side. But again, since we're using the default system, it means
we won't be able to connect directly to the machine. What we have to do is we
have to connect through a bastion host or an ssh jam host okay so this is
basically an intermediary machine that acts as a proxy any kind of git command
that we send has to go to this machine and then this machine will then forward
those commands to the newtron server so whenever we do git clone for example or
any kind of git command what will happen is your laptop will connect to the host so you need to
authenticate on the host and i'm going to show you a very easy way to do the authentication where you
won't have to specify your password every single time you connect to it and this will create using
ssh create an ssh tunnel and then through that tunnel the actual git command will go through
and then we'll connect to that machine.
Okay?
And again, this is for security reasons to make sure that
only people who have default accounts can actually access
the machine.
Okay?
All right.
So now let's go over those instructions.
So you can see what this means.
And what I'm going to do is I am going to actually implement
these instructions directly on this computer from scratch.
Perfect. So let's go to the instructions. So first step is you need to generate an SSH key pair.
So we'll talk very shortly because today we'll talk about security in distributed systems. So
we're going to go in a little bit more detail on how these public-private key pairs work.
But the way you can think about it, the SSH programs allows you to create a key pair. So
the key pair will contain a public key and a private key. By convention, the private key is
again a key that you keep for yourself and then the public key you can share with other computers
or with other users. Using this public private key schema actually allows you to authenticate
with the machine without having to insert a password. So the keys alone, the fact that you're
sharing the public key with someone, then that computer will share their public key with you,
then there will be an exchange of messages that will be encrypted between each other that allows
you to actually authenticate without having to put in a password or any passwords.
And only your computer, because it has that key, can authenticate on that machine.
Other computers cannot.
Maybe an analogy on how you can think about these public-private keys is, let's say you
want to build a mechanism where you want to allow your friends to send you messages in
a secure way.
Let's say that the messages are written on a piece of paper.
They're letters.
right so the way you can do this is by you know creating a mailbox where people
can go and put the letters and then sharing with your friends a bunch of
locks but you're the only person that has the key to those locks okay so the
locks act as the public keys these are things that you can share with everyone
if somebody wants to send a secure message to you you would write the
letter put it in the mailbox and then lock the mailbox with that lock so
since you're the only one that has the private key or the key you're the only
I can actually unlock the lock and read the message okay this is how again
conceptually we work so the first step is of course you need to generate an SSH
key pair so what I'm gonna do here let's assume that the terminal that I open
here will be from the guest computer so if you had a chance to read the known
programming assignment one I know that I mentioned the notion of a guest
machine. So what is the guest machine there and what is the difference between
the host and the guest machine?
Is it temporary?
The host is the mainframe and the guest is temporary?
I want to hear another answer.
Different privileges, like the guest doesn't have the ability to
go in and change other people's emails or something but the administrator or I
don't know that's just a guess time yeah those are not all good properties yes
we are using and the guest machine is that which we are trying to connect
perfect perfect so your answers were not incorrect you know you highlighted the
properties of the guest you know versus the host but what I was looking for is
that definition actually so right so by convention in programming assignment one
we said that the host machine is your own personal computer.
Could be your desktop computer, your laptop,
could be your own server that you have at home, right?
And on that computer, you will install a program called a hypervisor.
And the hypervisor will allow you to create a virtual machine.
We call that virtual machine a guest.
So the virtual machine is basically a software representation of a physical computer
in which you can install an OS, you can install programs,
you can do whatever you want.
so these instructions that i'm going to show you right now assume that i'm running them from your
virtual machine from your guest not from the local computer unfortunately i don't have a virtual
machine on this computer it will take me a long time to set it up so that's why i'm just going to
do it directly from this computer but imagine that the commands that i'm running right now you
would be running them from your virtual machine because you will clone your repository to the
virtual machine not to your host container okay all right so let's say
that again this is the terminal opening virtual machine let's assume that it's
Linux and I'm going to use Linux commands just because the
people behind PowerShell were kind enough to create aliases right from
Linux commands to the PowerShell command so I can just do Linux commands
here so and you let me know if the font is too small I can make it larger okay
Just feel free to interrupt me and say, hey, I cannot see.
You know, I'll make the fonts larger.
Okay.
So first step is, of course, we need to generate a public-private key pair.
To do this, SSH already provided a program that can help us do that.
The program is called SSH KeyGen.
And then what we'll do is we'll create a key using a specific encryption cipher.
This will be the ED25519 cipher.
So you can copy-paste the command, insert it in the command line, run, and this will generate a key.
Whenever you generate this public private key, it will ask you, where do you want to store this key?
So I'm just going to use the default location and the default name, so I'm going to press Enter.
You can set up a passphrase, which is kind of like an additional level of security
so that only the people that have the passphrase and the key can use the key.
But I'm just going to keep it blank for now just to make it easier.
okay so once you've pressed enter and you set up the team the program will tell
you that they've created a private key located in this path and then a public
key with the same name but the dot com extension so this will be your public
key that you can share with people and this is your private key that you do not
share with anyone all right so once you generated this key you can actually read
the contents of your public key by using the cat command cat stands for
concatenate. It basically allows you to read the contents of files or the output
programs. So I'm going to type in cat here and I'm gonna pass the path to my
public key and this will print my public key. So again this is a key I can share
with anyone. Oh great. This is the key that I need then to copy to GitLab and
then also to that bastion host. Okay? Alright so after this is done next step
Step number two, add your public key to the DePaul Jump host.
So to do this, DePaul has their own documentation because this is part of the DePaul infrastructure.
You can see more details if you go and access the website.
I'm going to zoom in here a little bit so we can all see the text better.
Okay, there's a few pieces of information here, a screenshot of what the interface looks like.
All you need to do to access the web interface that allows you to upload your public key to the JumpPost.
You need to access the keymanagement.sshjump.default.edu website.
And then you will need to log in using your Campus Connect credentials.
So I'm going to go ahead and log in here.
I'm already logged in D2L, so I just read my credentials here.
And then over here, you will open up an interface that will contain an empty box for you.
For me, I've already copy-pasted my keys over here, so I'm not going to override my keys.
But the first step would be to copy-paste your public key inside this box here and then click on Save to make sure that you copied your public key to the Bastion host.
Once that is done, you can move forward.
What I'm going to do here, since I have already a key that is copied, I'm going to copy my key from another machine on this machine.
so ignore this step is not something that you will need to do
all right very good so this would be step
number two will be complete you copy your key to the jump host now you need to add
your public key to the Neutron GitLab server. So to do this, again, you have an
example here on how to grab the contents of your key. I already have my contents
of my key over here. I'm going to copy it again. And then I'm going to go on my
favorite web browser and then I will connect to neutron.cbm.decall. This is
the GitLab server that you will be using for this pass. And then I'm going to log in using my credentials,
A small parenthesis here.
So after I created your account last night, you should have received an email to your school email address.
That contains instructions on how to set your password.
So make sure you go and set up a password there.
And then after you set your password, I highly recommend that you set up two-factor authentication.
You have, I think, a week to set up TwoFactor before you use access.
So make sure that you prioritize setting up TwoFactor.
TwoFactor authentication is basically another mechanism where it's more secure.
You authenticate using two separate mechanisms.
You put in a password and then you use an app on your phone.
So you can connect to your Google authenticator, for example, Microsoft Authenticated to implement
TwoFactor authentication.
So let me quickly log in as well here, we'll do that notification, let me see, oops, alright
very good so now that I'm logged in you will see a similar interface.
Let me zoom in here and the part that is important for us is that we want to copy our public
key to our account.
So to do that, you go in the top right corner and you click on preferences and then you
go to access and then SSH keys.
And then here you can add your key by clicking on the add new key button.
You can paste now the contents of your public key, so this was again the contents that I
copied from the command line terminal, you can give it a name, so if you have multiple
computers you can use the name of the computer, so if you have multiple keys on your computer
you can think about a naming schema, I'm just gonna call this one the name of the room that
I'm teaching.
Which was actually the computer from this one, and then I'm gonna choose that this is
just an authentication key, and I'm now gonna set up an expiration date for it, and then
I'm gonna add the key.
So now that the key is added, I can go to the next step and I can try to clone the repository.
There's one more thing that we have to do before that.
So again, in step number three, you add your public key to GitLab.
You follow these instructions and once you're done, you can go to step number four.
Now in step number four, what we will do is we will create a configuration file inside the .ssh folder.
So the SSH client application stores many of its user configurations inside this folder.
What we will do is we will create a special configuration to say that whenever we want to use the git command to clone or to push or to pull, and the Neutron server is the target server, we want to tell it to automatically use the ssh jump host that we also define in this configuration and use the keys to automatically authenticate between all of the machines so that we can have a seamless, let's say, experience.
when cloning the repository, when pushing and pulling to and from the repository.
Okay, so to do this, you can use your favorite text editor.
So in Linux, you will need to use some sort of command line text editor,
like Nano or Vim or Emacs, NeoVim.
Nano is the simplest one, so if you've never used a command line text editor before,
I highly recommend just using Nano.
Programming assignment 1 will be the only assignment where you need to use a text editor,
otherwise with programming assignment 2, I will show you how to connect your favorite
code editor or IDE to the virtual machine and do remote development.
So here, I don't have nano or vm on this machine, so I'm just going to use notepad
and I'm going to create a file here
and I'm going to copy paste
the contents of the configuration inside the file.
And then you will need to do some modifications here.
So for the jump host, you'll need to replace the username
with your actual Campus Connect or email address name
that you have set up by default.
In my case, it's A or here.
Here, I'm going to do a modification as well,
but you don't have to do it because you can use the same key.
In my case, I'm using two different keys, one key for the bastion host and then one key for the neutron server.
And then on the neutron side, I don't think you need to do any modifications.
So once you're done, save the file, close the file.
In this case, since I created the file using Notepad, Notepad, unfortunately, adds the txt extension,
so I'm going to have to rename the configuration file so that it doesn't have the txt extension.
All right, great, and then I can double check to see the contents of this file.
It has the proper configurations.
So this would be step number four.
If this file does not exist and you have to create it on Linux, make sure that it has
the proper permissions.
So for students that are familiar with the Linux Unix based system, what does this permission
say about this file?
So who can read and write?
Only the owner.
Perfect.
We'll talk about how these ownership are being set once we talk about security.
All right, so once you're done with that, you can test the connection and you can clone a repository.
So to do that, you can use the git clone command.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to go now to the repository.
For me, I don't have an actual repository, but I'm going to clone the skeleton called repository for programming assignment.
So I'm going to go to I think projects and then I can go to CSE 435.21 and then here you'll be able to see the skeleton code for this assignment. Now for programming assignment one, there's not a lot of skeleton code. There's only a readme that you have to fill out and then the code you have to generate according to whatever programming language you chose.
But then starting with programming assignment 2, I will actually generate some skeleton code for you, so you will start with a pre-existing codebase already.
And then you will need to update the codebase or extend the codebase to implement what's needed in programming assignments for you.
So here, the only thing that you will need to do in this assignment, make sure in the README you write your student name and email address,
the programming language that you chose for your solution,
and then instructions on how to compile and run the program.
You need to actually do this for all of the assignments.
The only difference is that Startable Programming Assignment 2,
I will include some instructions for you already.
You can change those instructions if need.
So, to clone the repository,
once you go to your repository on the web interface,
in the right portion, you can click on Code,
And then here will have an option to clone the repository.
Now, for some reason, let me see if I zoom out a little bit because it's cutting off this portion here.
All right. So you can clone using SSH.
Let me see if I can zoom back in now.
That's hiding away for some reason when I zoom in that text.
But you can clone either using SSH or HTTPS.
If you choose HTTPS, you don't need to do anything special.
However, note that you will not be able to authenticate using your password.
You need to generate an authentication token.
If this is something else, I'll leave it for you to read if you want to use it.
My recommendation is that you use SSH to clone your repository.
So you will copy the URL of your repository.
And then after you copy the URL, you go to your command line and you type in git clone.
and then you paste the URL. The URL has a, let's see, defined structure. So it contains the DNS
name of the GitLab server that we have for this class. And then it contains the name of the project
and then the name of the group and of the subgroup in which your repository will reside. So this
will be a little bit different. For you it will be cse435 slash fall 2026 slash cse435pa1 dash
and then your username. Okay but I'm cloning the skeleton code or the template code. That's it.
And then you click on clone. So when you clone the repository since I'm connecting now for the
first time to the bastion host this is what this message is saying is setting up a fingerprint.
So you want to type in yes to set up the fingerprint.
And then after that, it will ask me for the passphrase that I have for my key that I'm
using to authenticate on the bastion host.
If you didn't set up a passphrase, the system will not ask anything of you.
And then once you put a passphrase, it will now connect to the neutron server.
So if you remember, like in the diagram, connect first to the bastion host, authenticate,
and through the SSH tunnel connect to the neutron server.
You need to, since I'm connecting for the first time,
set up the fingerprint, type in yes,
and then your repository will be cloned.
Once you see receiving objects 100% and done,
it means that your repository was cloned successfully.
So I can check to see the contents by running LS.
I have here a folder called CSE 435 PA1, right?
I can go inside that folder and I can see that I have a readme.
okay so these are again the instructions that you will need to follow to set up
let's see the SSH configuration part but once that is set up you can just go
ahead and clone your repositories for the rest of the assignment using the
simple git clone git push gip pull commands okay any questions regarding
you know connecting to GitLab I'm working on two machines at home I'm just going to
need to install two VMs and key pairing for each of them?
Sure, if you want to.
So there's a bunch of solutions, and they're all perfectly valid.
So if you're going the path of two VMs, by recommendation,
generate two public-private keys, one for one VM, one for the other one.
And then make sure that you follow these instructions for both of them
so you can have that configuration file set up.
And then you can just clone the repository, push and pull between them.
now if you want to do something more interesting you know you could set up
one of your machines to have the VM and then the other computer maybe connect to
the VM to the secondary computer so anyways up to you it depends on how
creative you wanna be yes if you have multiple VMs but you want to work from
you will need to generate your own that's the best practice
And access to one in the other ?
Exactly, exactly.
Yeah, so you can give it a try, you know, and see what it would take to do that.
You might need to, you know, enable some ports in the firewall of your host computers, right.
You need to open them up and then forward them so that whenever you connect to your machine,
it actually forwards the connection to your virtual machine.
OK.
If you want to do it and you're encountering difficulties, you know, just let me know.
I'll be glad to help you debug it during our time.
Okay?
All right.
Any other questions?
If I've already created the public private key
from the host to the virtual machine,
there's nothing special I have to do
for them to coexist, correct?
No, no.
There's nothing special.
Just keep in mind that when you clone your repository,
you want to clone it on the virtual machine.
So make sure that you use the keys on the virtual machine,
not from the host.
I know there's a step in part one
where you need to connect from the host
to the virtual machine.
So the host will also have its own public-private key pair.
But that's not the one that you will be using to clone the repository.
The passphrase act like a root password in Linux, or it's just for the first time?
No.
So for me, the passphrase is because I wanted to secure my key.
So they have an additional layer of security.
If somebody steals, for example, your private key, right, if you add this passphrase,
if they don't have the passphrase,
then they cannot use that part of private key.
So it's good practice as well
whenever you generate public private keys
to also add a passphrase as well.
But for the purpose of the assignments in this class,
it's totally fine if you just leave them without a passphrase.
So I was going to say regarding generating these keys
and connecting to machines using these keys,
this is what it's a pretty standard approach
for connecting to remote machines.
So whenever you're creating, for example,
a virtual machine on Amazon AWS or Azure or Google Cloud Platform,
especially if it's a Linux machine
without any kind of graphical user interface.
The way that you would connect to them would be through SSH.
And a lot of the times they don't allow you
to actually connect using passwords or authentication keys.
They would actually ask you to upload a public key on your system.
So if you become comfortable with this process,
you will then be able to transfer it
whenever you're going to use cloud resources.
And I know that a lot of people are using cloud resources nowadays to prototype things, so it will be very useful.
And we'll be using this as well once we go on Programming Assembly.
And then for Programming Assembly, we'll allow you to use Chameleon Cloud.
And I'll talk more about it.
This is a National Science Foundation-sponsored cloud built for research and education.
So we can use it to learn more about how to use cloud resources.
But those are optional for this class.
Okay?
Any other questions?
Alright very good. If at some point I'm going too fast, just let me know. I'll go dislocked.
Alright very good. So with this said, what I'm going to do actually, I want to remove
my key from this computer and that folder as well and then we can move on.
So again, if you download the assignment, there's a version 2 of the PDF which should
you mentioned now the new deadline for S deck, yes?
I was wondering like for this course, are there like any prerequisites that we need to complete first?
Yeah so the class itself has a number of
Last Thursday like I had the class for object oriented Java.
He also mentioned that there are a few prerequisites, but like he didn't specify where we need to access the reading material and all that.
Okay, so for this class, as it's mentioned in the syllabus, right, the prerequisites for this class are data structures too and systems too. So it depends, you know, if maybe you've transferred from somewhere, right, sometimes they get waived.
So the most important aspect there is that in this class,
there are four programming languages that I support.
YC++, Java, Go, and Rust.
So feel free to choose any programming language you want for this class.
Sometimes students choose a programming language that they're more comfortable with.
That's totally fine. You won't lose anything.
Sometimes people want to learn a new programming language.
And on the extreme case, I've had students who did the assignments in all programming languages
because they wanted to learn the particularities of all the languages.
but it's up to you how hardcore you want to be okay but what's important so
right so systems and data structures so data structures whatever programming
language you choose try to refresh yourself the concepts on how to create
some of the basic data structures in that language so in this class I'm not
going to ask you to build data structures from scratch right you're not going to
build hash tables from scratch or trees binary trees from scratch right you can
use the existing standard library as long as you don't need extra packages so again they usually
the standard library comes pre-compiled these methods so again use those use those because we're
going to build more complex applications in this class but you need to know how to use them right
so you need to know the basics and how the most important data structure for this class is actually
the hash table data structure and talking about that you know can somebody tell me what is a
hash table data structure? What are the properties? What do we use it for?
And imagine any kind of question that I'm asking here, imagine that you had
a kid from kindergarten come and ask you, like, hey, what's a hash table? So you can use your
own language to explain. Yes? It's like a structure that
stores key value pairs? Key value pairs. And I need more.
So what are the properties? So we can store key value pairs, but there's a very important
properties that makes hash tables different from, for example, lists or vectors.
Amortized constant retrievals and inserts.
Perfect.
And deletions as well, right?
So constant means, right, if you've heard of the big O notation, right, O of 1, right?
So what does O of 1 mean?
Intuitive.
Time complexity.
So it's time.
Yeah.
But what does time complexity mean intuitively?
What does it tell me when I have O of 1?
What do I understand in the mirror, right?
So that's O of n linear, right?
So it increases with the number of elements, yes?
It takes the same amount of work,
no matter how big the input size is.
Exactly, exactly, right?
So from a computational point of view, right,
it takes one step to do an insertion or a deletion
or a removal.
No, deletion is the same.
Lookup, lookup.
so for example if I want to insert an element in a list
I have to traverse the list
so we say it's O of N
N being the number of elements
so I'm doing N discrete steps
before I can insert a piece of data at the end of the list
or when I search for an element in the list
if they're not sorted
I need to go element by element
and see if the element is in the list
so that's also O of N
O of N means the worst case scenario
All right, very good. Now we will see throughout the assignments that even though in practice the hash tables have a time complexity, theoretical complexity of O of 1, in practice there are different kinds of side effects that can interfere with performance.
and that's what you will see in programming assignments 3 and moving on, okay?
And you need to measure that difference in performance as well.
Okay, very good.
And then when it comes to systems, what's very important is I'd like you to try to refresh
a little bit your memory about the basic components of a computer, right?
So if I were to ask you right now, again, somebody from kindergarten, you know,
what are the basic components of any computer, right?
It doesn't matter if it's a smartphone, a laptop, a desktop computer, right?
What are some of the common components that you find in all of them, and the most important?
Yes.
CPU.
So CPU, what's the purpose of the CPU?
What does it do?
To do the mathematical operations.
Correct, it does mathematical operations.
What else does the CPU do?
So it does arithmeticological operations, check.
Does it do the scheduling?
So that's more of the kernel and the operating system that are scheduling programs.
or processes.
But what does, again, at a very basic level,
what does the CPU do?
Communicates with the RAM?
It can communicate with the RAM, yes.
But there's also, so I would say...
Is it software with a RAM?
Say it again?
And it's a software with a RAM.
Correct, at a very high level.
But I'm looking at a little bit lower level.
So we can say that the CPU executes instructions.
One type of instruction is, of course,
arachemetical logical instructions.
But what other kind of instructions can it do?
That's what I was going to say, do machine instructions.
Machine instructions, right.
So, we have the arithmeticological, but there's also two more types of instructions that are very popular.
We all use it all the time.
Read writes.
Read writes, right.
So, again, the CPU, right, whenever it does an execution instruction, especially arithmeticological ones, right, it does the operations on registers.
That's very fast memory, right, but the data does not reside on the processor because registers are very small.
It needs to do load and store operations to and from the memory.
So to bring data from the memory to the registers.
So that would be data movement instruction.
And then another kind of instruction.
So how does the CPU execute the instructions?
In which order?
Of course.
So all of the languages, right?
They compile the code to machine code, right?
But then, right, what is the sequence of those instructions?
How does the processor execute them?
In what sequence?
In order unless there's a jump?
In order unless there's a jump, right?
So it executes them one by one in increasing number of memory address.
We say that, again, they execute instruction sequential, right?
But we also have that third type of instructions, which is the control flow of instructions.
So these allow us to actually tell the processor, hey, go and execute another instruction from a different address from the program.
And those instructions are either the branch or the jump instructions or conditional jump.
We have various kinds of instructions out there depending on the architecture.
Okay, so the CPU is one very important component.
That's what the CPU does.
What other components we find in a token computer, in a single node computer?
Yes?
Memory.
What is your name?
Zach.
Perfect.
So memory.
What kind of memory can we have in a computer?
Like RAM versus like...
Yes.
Yes, yes, yes, yes.
So RAM versus hard drive.
Or another way to say it, right?
It's main memory versus secondary storage.
Right?
Also, what is the property or what is the difference between RAM and hard drive?
The main difference.
Ram and also?
Yes, exactly.
So RAM is volatile while secondary storage, either hard drives or solid-state drives,
those are persistent.
What does it mean that it's volatile?
As soon as it loses power, it flushes everything.
Exactly.
So as we lose power, when the computer starts again, those memory cells, they get initialized
randomly depending on the noise in the system.
So if we had some data, if we unplugged the computer, let's say it doesn't have some sort
of battery like a laptop.
Right. If we unplug the computer, then everything gets lost from the RAM.
We have to reload the operating system, reload the program, start from scratch.
Well, secondary storage can store the data per system.
Now, the disadvantage, right, secondary storage is that it's usually way slower than main memory.
So what we want to do is we want to bring the data.
If you remember the memory hierarchy from the previous classes, we want to bring data from very slow, high capacity devices closer and closer to the CPU.
Right. OK, perfect.
So these are the things that I'd like you to keep in mind.
And then there's one more type of components that we have in the computer.
So we have the CPU.
We have memory.
And I'm going to add another type of component, which is the motherboard that interconnects everything.
But then we also have some additional devices, right?
And we call these input-output devices.
Right.
So these are the devices that allow either users or other computers to interact with the computer system.
So input-output devices could mean keyboards, mice, touchpad, displays, but it can also mean network cards, hard drives, accelerators like GPUs.
Although the GPUs, they're not really classified as an input-output device, they're more classified as an accelerator, so an extension to the CPU.
Okay, very good. So this is what I'd like you to have in mind, because in this class, when we learn about distributed systems, and we'll talk today about size scalability,
We will learn that, again, one of the reasons why we want to build distributed systems is to improve the performance of a service or to be able to provide a service to increasing number of users.
And a lot of the times, the limitations have to do with these exact components inside our system.
So sometimes maybe the application that we're building requires a lot of memory.
So this means that we want to add more computers connected to a network to make a distributed system in order to increase the memory capacity.
Or sometimes maybe needs more computational power, right?
So we add more processing power, no GPUs, more CPUs.
We have examples already, right?
The memory is needed by AI applications nowadays, right?
To be able to load models on your system, right?
You need a lot of RAM.
You can do that by either buying a very expensive, you know,
single-node computer with a lot of RAM.
Or you can go, let's say, the cheaper way, you know,
and to deploy multiple machines and then combine the RAM
by connecting those machines over the network.
There are advantages and disadvantages for running either a solution.
For the computationally intensive applications, think about cryptocurrency mining.
They needed devices like GPUs to do the calculations very fast.
So this will be an example where we want to build more computers and create a distributed system
so we can compute those hashes faster and mine Bitcoin faster so we can earn more.
Anyways, these are just examples.
So to go back to your question regarding prerequisites.
So again, data structures and systems.
Try to refresh a little bit your memory over these concepts.
Now, if you want, I do have a few links that are not on D2L.
If you need, you know, some tutorials for your favorite programming language,
for Go and Rust, you'll be able to go to their website.
They have very good tutorials there.
For C++, I have a very good resource that is not very well known,
so just reach out to me over email and I'll share that resource.
And then for Java, I also have another website that is also not very well known,
but it's the official website where you learn all of the basic data structures that you use in any Java program.
Okay?
These courses, these are available on D2L, or like I need to add them separately on Campus Connect?
No, so these are not courses.
These are just some external resources.
So they're just some websites that are available for everyone.
But...
How do you access these on D2L?
No, so for the programming languages, email me, and then I'll tell you.
Not exactly the programming languages, but these ones?
These ones, like the Linux shell, Ubuntu Server documentation,
Gitguide, these are already links inside D2L.
If you go under content...
In the system, then the systems that you showed.
Oh I see. So for these ones, no, these are courses.
So in order to access these resources,
my recommendation is that you reach out to the professors
that are currently teaching those courses
and see if they would be willing to add you as an auditing student.
So, you can see what they are.
Okay.
But, yeah, you need to reach out to the professors that are teaching those courses.
I did this quarter.
Okay.
Any other questions?
All right.
Very good.
So, then.
Okay.
So, this is the prerequisites.
We talked about programming assignment one.
GitLab accounts.
Very good.
So, let's go ahead and continue talking about distributed systems.
So I think if I remember right, in the lecture recording, we define what a distributed system is.
So again, try to keep in mind this definition because everything that we talk ties back to this definition.
So again, we say that a distributed system is a collection of independent computers that appears to its users as a single coherent system.
It's two very important properties.
Independent computers are a network.
It means each computer has its own state, each computer has its own hardware operating system, software stack, right?
And then we make them all work together, right?
We connect them, we implement communication but also coordination between them so that they appear to the user as if it's one single system they access.
And we do this through interfaces in the middleware.
We also talked about the difference between decentralized and distributed systems, okay?
So in quizzes and in the exam, if I ask you what is the definition of a distributed system, you go here and you pick this definition from Andrew Tannabal.
Now, if I ask you when I want to highlight the difference between distributed and decentralized, you want to use the definitions from this slide.
So we define decentralized system as a network computer system in which the processes and resources are necessarily spread.
So they are distributed because of some sort of necessity.
We gave, I think, as examples, federated learning where we have multiple hospitals, each having their own database.
And the reason why we have a distributed system is because we need to interconnect this database in order to move the training algorithms to the databases because we cannot move the data because of HIPAA reasons.
right?
So because the data that is in those hospitals,
right,
pertain to people,
to clients,
to patients there,
it needs to be protected.
So it cannot simply be moved around to another data center to do AI
training.
So what we do is we move the AIs near the hospitals,
we do training there,
and then we aggregate the data.
So we have,
again,
a system for doing this distributed AI learning,
in a sense,
or AI training,
because we cannot move the data from those machines.
So out of necessity,
we have a distributed system.
The same applies for blockchain technologies, okay?
So, right, we wanted to build this distributive, right, ledger system because we cannot trust one bank with all of our transactions, right?
We want to build it in a way where no one entity can control all of the transactions without having everyone be able to verify it, okay?
And then a distributive system is defined as a network computer system in which processes and resources are sufficiently spread.
So this is the case of, let's say, Gmail.
When Google built the Gmail system, they initially built it for their own engineers so that they can communicate with each other and synchronize because they have an international team that was working on it.
But then they decided to provide this service for everyone else for various reasons.
So now all of a sudden they had to add more computers to their network computer system
in order to be able to serve everyone the services behind Gmail.
So out of sufficiency, they only added a sufficient number of computers
in order to, for example, maybe provide Gmail to half of the population of the world.
And that's where they stopped.
Okay.
We also talked about some misconceptions there.
I'm not going to go into details here.
the different perspectives
which we study distributed systems.
So after chapter one,
we'll go into architectures
and then we talked about the design.
So similarly to the way,
you know, whenever people build
or build some sort of software
or I'll give the example
of operating systems, right?
We have many operating systems out there,
right?
We have Windows,
we have Mac OS,
Android, iOS, right?
Linux distributions.
Right.
And we have so many because they were all built for specific purposes.
In the end, an operating system.
Right.
It doesn't matter which one you pick.
You know, it still implements some sort of general goal, but then they have been specialized.
You know, can somebody tell me if you remember from your systems class, you know, what is
the purpose of the operating system?
Why do we need it?
Yes.
yes
usability
usability right so right
the operating system acts as an
interface right between human
users and then the hardware
right the hardware if you remember from your previous
classes right uses these very
weird protocols right
machine instructions
right which are very hard for humans to read
and if you think about it right the way the
computers are organized with CPU memory
buses right
Other devices, right, PCIe devices, I.O. devices, right, it would be very hard for a user to, like, keep everything in their minds of how do I use the system.
So what the operating system does, it creates a set of abstractions that everyone can understand, right?
Those abstractions are tied to the actual components of the computer, right?
You have processes for CPU.
So the programs that are running, right, we run them under the form of processes.
And each process, right, has the impression that it's the only process using the processor, right, the CPU.
We also have virtual memory.
That's another abstraction, right?
It also helps each program have the impression that they have access to the entire memory space of the computer.
But in reality, right, that virtual memory gets translated to the physical addresses.
We'll go back over it because we have a dedicated chapter on processes.
So we'll go over those details again.
And then in order to abstract the notion of input-output devices, in the case of the Linux operating system, they use the notion of files.
So the mouse is a file, the keyboard is a file, and we can read data.
The display is a file where we write data to it.
So these are the three main abstractions that the operating system uses in order to build that interface.
Now, like I said, we have many operating systems out there, Windows, macOS.
So, for example, these operating systems were built with the goal of providing, again, a seamless, responsive interface.
That's their purpose.
They were built to, again, not be laggy, to be beautifully colored, intuitive for the users.
In the case of Linux distributions, the purpose was to build a very simple kernel that can help people learn about operating systems
and you can learn people run programs
without the overhead of the graphical user interfaces, for example.
Or the overhead of other applications out there.
This is one of the main reasons why Linux is very popular in distributed systems
because it's so lightweight, but also because it's open source
so people can tune it, can modify it, can make it serve whatever purpose they have.
So, similarly to operating systems,
whenever people build distributed systems,
there are, of course, many goals that they try to achieve,
what we did
in the recording, I think we started
talking about some of the general
problems that can be found. The first
one being the support
for sharing of resources or why
one of the main reasons we want to build
distributed systems is because we have many
computers and we want to figure out a way
how do we use those resources efficiently?
How do we give the user access to
multiple computers simultaneously without
maybe them being aware of those
resources? Distribution transparency
was another goal, so we wanted to hide away the fact that there are multiple computers.
Google Drive does this very well.
When you access a document in Google Drive, you don't know in which data center, in which
server, on which hard drive in that server the data resides.
It's done very transparently for you.
It actually gives you the impression that those files actually reside on your computer.
That's what Google tries to say even with Google Chrome and the Chromebooks.
They want to say that, oh, you can have this computer
that is always connected to the cloud, right?
So it's as if you have all of the files locally,
but actually they reside on the cloud
and they're just cached on your computer.
All right, then openness, of course, right?
The openness goal refers to, again,
building systems that are maintainable.
You can extend them easily.
They can easily interoperate with another system.
That's very important.
I think we talked about dependability as well.
So the main concept there is that a distributed system is made out of multiple components.
And actually, let me go to dependability so I can provide you another perspective on how to understand this concept.
And I'm going to make a small parenthesis here.
and I'm going to talk about engineering in the world of computers.
And I'm not just referring to computer engineering
because I know you can go and study computer engineering, right?
And it refers to studying the hardware, right?
And then you can do software engineering.
So when I say engineering, I mean both of them, okay?
So engineering is the task of solving problems
or building products or applications, right?
And they have a certain methodology that they follow.
So in, let's say, software engineering, before they build anything, they have to actually define either what the problem is that they're solving or the product that they're building.
So they do this by writing a specification.
So once you're going to go, if you already have experience, then you already know what I'm talking about.
but if they haven't worked yet for a company,
you will see that one of the main important steps
is that you need to work on a specification
or a document that actually defines the product
that you're creating or the problem that you are solving.
So you spend a lot of time defining a document
as best as you can.
Then after that follows the software development
or the implementation of the product
or the implementation of the application
that solves the problem, right?
So that's the fun part.
We all like to do it, right?
AIs can do it 50 times faster than us.
You know, that's all great.
That was never really a problem.
But then the next challenge is making sure that the software that was created actually
works according to that specification.
So a lot of the time we spend it actually in doing testing or verification to make sure
that the application works according to its specification.
Okay, so when it comes to distributed systems, they also have a specification as well.
Now, the only, let's say, complicating thing is that distributed systems have many components that are connected in very interesting ways.
And let's say the distributed system itself or the services, they actually depend on those components working well.
And for those components to actually work also according to their own specification.
So we say that a distributed system, it's a big system that is made out of multiple components, but that the distributed system depends on the correctness of those components that it's made of.
All right. So, dependability refers to building systems that, again, work well and function well because, again, the system itself depends on other components.
And I think what we did in the lecture recording, I talked about some of the metrics that people use to measure dependability.
You can go and just rewatch the lecture for these.
But the concept itself is that, again, a distributive system is made out of multiple components
and the correctness of the distributive system depends on the correctness of those components.
We sometimes see this as well even when you do software engineering with small programs.
You will be using, for example, the standard library to implement applications.
So the correctness of your program also depends on the correctness of the implementation of those standard libraries.
And that's why I want you to stay with the standard libraries and not use any other package that you find on the internet because they might have bugs.
And those bugs will trickle in your application.
So they will create bugs in your application.
So the same principle applies but at a larger scale.
All right.
And then I think the lecture recording ended on the security goal.
Okay?
So this is where we will start today.
Let me see what time is it.
Okay, we still have a few minutes before we take a break.
The way that I choose this class is usually one hour and a half, we take a 15-minute break, and then we come back for almost an hour and a half.
So, security, it's another general goal when it comes to implementing distributed systems.
It makes sense, because a distributed system is a collection of independent computers that are connected over a network.
When we send data over the network, if we're not very careful, we might send the data over plain text.
If our distributed system is geographically distributed, we might send plain text data over the internet.
So somebody could intercept it and steal the data and then, you know, create security breaches in our system.
So it's very important, right, that we secure the system and that we secure the components that makes up the distributed system.
We can also say, right, that a distributed system that is not secure, right, can be compromised, which then is not dependable anymore.
So it can also affect the dependability goal as well.
Now, I just want to make another small parenthesis here.
In this class, the only extent that we will focus when it comes to security
will be what's covered in the introductory chapter, so in the first chapter.
There are a lot of classes offered at default in terms of cybersecurity,
computer security that you can take where you'll learn way more many things
that are in this class about how to secure computers, networks, and clusters of computers.
But I just want to highlight some of the more important, let's say, mechanisms and technologies
that are relevant for distributed systems.
So when it comes to security, what we typically want to implement is two things.
Now, again, if you've already taken a computer security class,
you're going to contradict me.
There's other things that you want.
But for the purpose of distributed systems, let's just look at these two things.
So we want to implement typically confidentiality and integrity.
Confidentiality refers to disclosing information only to authorized parties, right?
So only the people that are authorized to access the information can access the information.
And then integrity refers to ensuring that alterations to assets of a system can be made only in an authorized way.
So, iterations to, you know, the configuration of a system to data, information, structure, right, can all be done in an authorized way.
So, to do this, when it comes to security, in order to achieve confidentiality and integrity, we usually use three mechanisms.
So, these are three abstract mechanisms that can be implemented in various ways.
Authentication, of course, is a very important mechanism.
authentication refers to verifying the correctness of a claim identity.
So for example, whenever you're connecting to a remote machine,
including your virtual machine, you have to authenticate first.
And you're using the username-password combo.
You can also use, if you want, username and public-private key combo as well
to implement authentication.
There are various ways authentication can be implemented
in order to achieve, let's say, a high degree of security.
Another mechanism is authorization.
So authorization refers to verifying if an entity has the proper access rights.
You've already encountered this as well.
Well, once you start working on part one and part two, you will encounter it.
Basically, a form of authorization could be file permissions.
So the file permissions can be used to say which entity is allowed to access which resources in what way.
There's also access control lists, role-based access control.
There's all different kinds of forms that are very popular, especially in web applications.
And then lastly, the last mechanism is trust.
So trust refers to the property that an entity can be assured that another will perform particular actions according to a specific expectation.
So this means that, let's say that I have a username called AORHian and I'm logging into a server, right?
The server will assume that the user that logged in as AORHian, right, is the actual user that is supposed to access that machine.
If somebody steals my credentials and logs in as AORHian, right, then they can go and do the things that I can do, but they can also do malicious things on the machine as well.
So, right, so trust, again, refers to how do we verify to make sure that, you know, an entity that says who they are, you know, can access the machine and can work according to their, let's say, expectations, right?
if somebody steals my credentials, they're probably going to do things very differently than what I'm doing.
They're going to defer in terms of a pattern of access.
So there are tools out there that can actually monitor this kind of access
and then can identify if somebody, you know, does things that they're not supposed to do in the system
or that it's different from their typical behavior.
But usually, in practice, trust is very hard to implement
because you don't have complete information.
And because of the nature of how we authenticate to the machines, it's very hard.
I think people nowadays, they try to tie, for example, authentication to biometric information like, you know, fingerprints, you know, that way they will give you a mechanism that is going to be harder to trick in a sense.
But in the end, this is all digital computers, you know, so it's very hard to build a perfect system.
Okay.
And that's why people usually focus when it comes to trust on detecting unusual behavior.
Of course, these are abstract mechanisms.
But when it comes to the actual practical mechanisms or implementation security, the most popular ones, of course, is using encryption and decryption.
Can somebody tell me, you know, using your own words, especially if you've already taken these classes, you know, what is encryption?
Or how would you explain, you know, to somebody from Kidding Carter what encryption does?
Yes.
What is your name?
Tarak, you said?
Okay, fair.
plain text and converting it into like non-human readable format And why do we wanna do this?
Yeah, they cannot extract the information, right so again if you want to for example
send data from one person to another, we wanna make sure that nobody can read that data so
what we do is we do some sort of encryption, right if we wanna store data somewhere and
Only the person that stored the data can access that data.
We also use encryption.
So, again, it's a mechanism that allows us to transform data, like you said, from plain text,
where all of the information is readable, to some sort of ciphertext,
where basically there's no leak of the information from the original plain text data.
The way encryption and decryption systems work is by using, of course, keys.
Keys can be implemented in various ways.
a lot of times they follow some sort of mathematical formula to generate some numbers
that then can be used to implement encryption and decryption algorithms.
Now when it comes to encryption, there are two types of, let's say, encryption schemas out there.
Symmetric key encryption schemas and then asymmetric key encryption schemas.
symmetric key encryption schemas are a type of schemas that use the same key to do both encryption and decryption
that key is typically called a secret key
it's a key that you generate once and then you can use it to both encrypt and decrypt the data
so basically you have two separate functions
an E function for encryption, a D function for decryption
and you can apply encryption and decryption over some sort of data
using the key K.
And the property is that if you have a piece of data
and you encrypt it with a key K and then you decrypt that result,
it should give you back the original data.
There are many symmetric key encryption schemas out there
that have been created.
They're very powerful ones that are very hard to break
even for the realm of quantum computing, let's say.
So however, there is one main disadvantage and the main drawback of the system doesn't have to do with the algorithms used behind.
It has more to do with how do we disseminate this key?
How do we transfer this key from one entity to another?
So let's say that I want to talk with my friend Lucian, right?
And in order to communicate with him, you know, in an encrypted fashion, we would generate a secret key, but I need to transfer that key to my friend, Gucci, so then if I transfer it, for example, over the internet, right, if somebody is, you know, monitoring the traffic and, you know, sniffing the traffic, let's say, you know, they can intercept my key, steal my key, and then they can also decrypt and encrypt, you know, the messages using the exact same thing.
So this is one of the main challenges.
How do we send those keys in a very secure way?
Some people might want to say that, well, you can put the key on a flash drive and you can drive there to your friend and drop the key there.
But if they live in Australia and I'm in the US, then that would be a very expensive flight just to share some keys.
So this is why people started thinking about other ways to build encryption.
and this takes us to the second kind of encryption schema,
which is the asymmetric key encryption schema.
So in asymmetric, instead of using one single key,
these systems, they use two keys.
They use a public key and a private key,
or sometimes also called a secret key as well.
So in these key encryption schemas,
we, of course, still use mathematical models
to generate now two numbers that are related to each other,
And the interesting relation is that if you have a piece of data,
you can either encrypt or decrypt the data using either of the keys.
But if you use one of the keys to encrypt the data,
you have to use the other key to decrypt the data.
So if I'm using, for example, the secret key to encrypt the data,
I need to then use the public key to decrypt the data.
But I can also use the public key to encrypt the data,
which means that when I apply the secret key,
the algorithm with the secret key should give me back the data.
They should decrypt the data.
So this can be expressed under the form here.
If you ignore this bullet point, right,
if I have a piece of data and I encrypt it using the public key,
let's say, of Bob, and then I apply again the decryption algorithm
using the secret key of Bob, I should get back the same data.
So what's very interesting about this public-private key encryption scheme
is that it actually bypasses that security issue
that symmetric key encryption schema keys have.
So now, if, for example, I want to share the key with somebody else
so I can implement secure communication,
I can share within the public key,
and even if the malicious entity has the public key,
the system will still work,
as long as I keep my secret key secret or my private key private.
All right.
So, for example, here,
Let's see if Alice wants to send a message to Bob.
What Alice needs to do, Alice needs to get a copy of the public key from Bob.
Once it has access to that key, Alice can encrypt the message that he wants to send to Bob using Bob's public key.
Kind of similar to the analogy that I made earlier.
So if Alice wants to send a message, he needs to grab a lock from Bob, puts the message in the mailbox, locks it with a lock.
so it encrypts the data using Bob's puppy key.
And then since Bob is the only entity that has access to the private key of Bob,
only Bob can decrypt that data.
So when Bob receives the message,
he can use the secret key from Bob to decrypt the data
and he has access to whatever message Alice sent to Bob.
Now, there's also some problems here as well.
So one of the main problems that appears
is that how do we guarantee that if a message is sent by someone,
let's say from Alice,
how do we guarantee that when I decrypt the message
that the message actually came from Alice
and not from somebody impersonating Alice?
So let's say I have Trudy there, right,
who also gets a copy of Bob's public key somehow, right,
and they encrypt the message and they send the message before Alice does.
How does Bob know then that the message came from Trudy and not Alice?
So for this, we need to figure out a way to implement a very old technique that was used, you know, even during medieval times, which is the ability to sign the messages, right?
So you sign them in a way where you can validate where the message came from.
The way people used to do this during medieval times, right, if a lord wanted to write, you know, to another king, you know, a message, they would write a letter, put it in, write an envelope, and then seal the envelope with some sort of stamp and wax, right, and then somebody broke that envelope, it means, oh, somebody tampered with the message.
But if, you know, the seal was still there, then it means nobody tampered, and by looking at the seal, they were very, you know, intricate, you know, the seals, we can validate who actually sent that seal.
So in digital systems we can do the same thing by actually using both pairs of public private keys from both Alice and Bob.
So how do we attach some sort of signature to the message?
Well let's say again Alice wants to send a message to Bob.
Alice will get a copy of Bob's public key.
But Alice will also share her public key with Bob as well.
So now they both have access to each other's public keys.
So what Alice will do, Alice will prepare a message.
The message will contain the actual message or the data that Alice wants to send to Bob.
And then in addition to the data, it will also contain another ciphertext.
And the ciphertext is obtained by encrypting the data using Alice's secret key.
All right, so we send the data, the data encrypted using Alice's secret key.
And then what we do is we encrypt this entire bigger message using Bob's public key.
Right, so we have a huge, you know, a blob encrypted.
We send it to Bob.
Now Bob has access to Alice's public key, but also to his own secret key.
So what we do is by using Bob's secret key, we decrypt the message.
We can see the data that was sent by Alice.
And then what we do is over the ciphertext that was sent by Alice, we apply the public key of Alice.
And if we do that, this would be the equivalent of encrypting the data using Alice's secret key
and then decrypting the data using Alice's public key should give us back a copy of the data.
And as long as these two pieces of data are the same, it means that the data came from Alice.
This is what SSH is using when you're setting public-private key-based authentication.
You are copying your public key on the server.
When you use SSH, the server automatically copies a public key in your program
and then they exchange some messages between each other
and that's how authentication is achieved, right?
Using the exact same, let's say, message signing mechanism that we saw here.
Okay?
So, to implement, again, secure communication with validation of authenticity, right?
We implement signatures basically on both machines.
We generate public, public keys.
We share the public keys between the two machines.
And then we send a few challenging messages to validate that the encryption is done successfully.
And when it's done, it means that we have valid authentication and we can have a secure channel for sending here.
Now, there's also another problem here.
So the problem is if we want to sign the messages by sending the data
and then also an encrypted variant of the data,
where basically whenever we have to send, let's say, one gigabyte of data,
we need to duplicate that data because we have to send the encrypted version.
So we will send one gigabyte of data, which will be encrypted using Bob's public key,
but then another one gigabyte of data,
which will be encrypted using Alice's secret key plus Bob's public key as well.
So this doubles the amount of data that I have to send for each message,
which is not very efficient.
So we want to implement this in a little bit more efficient way.
So this takes us to the second practical mechanism
that is used to implement security, especially in distributed systems,
which is secure hashing.
Now, before I talk about secure hashing,
I know we talked about hash tables earlier.
And we know that hash tables also use a hash function.
But what is a hash function?
Or what are the properties of a hash function?
Yes.
It runs some mathematical operation over the data
to yield a unique identifier or value.
Unique identifier, yeah.
That's good.
So it does some transformation from an input to an output.
What can you tell me about the input and the output?
The inputs usually transform with like a prime number.
The hash function uses a prime number to transform the input from the input to an output.
But I was interested more in terms of the size of the input and the output.
Usually it hashes to like something smaller and it always gives the same output?
Yes, or not the same sized output but not the same output.
So a very important property of a hash function is that it can receive a variable-sized input,
but it always generates a fixed-size output.
So it does a transformation.
Now, let's say if I know the output of a hash function,
can I determine which input generated that output?
Why not?
So because the hash function, the output which we are getting is not the data which we input.
It's just the mathematical function or the value which it calculated.
So we cannot go back towards the data which we gave in that code.
I hope it makes sense.
I wasn't able to.
Right, let's see your answer as well.
I was just going to say, because we trust that the hash function itself will encrypt it.
We don't trust it.
So actually, there's an even simpler explanation, right?
So think about in mathematical terms.
They call it, you know, one-to-one correspondence, right?
So the hash function, they don't have one-to-one correspondence.
So the input space is infinite, because you can have variable size inputs, right?
There's no limit on how big an input can be.
Of course, if you have something that is super large, you won't be able to do the calculation on time.
But technically, algorithmically, the input can be of any size, right?
So you have an infinite space of input data points, right?
But the output space is fixed in size.
So there's a discrete number of data points that can be mapped from the input to the output
whenever you apply a hash function.
So what happens, and I'm sure you've heard about this,
when you build a hash table, right, you have collisions.
when multiple inputs actually lead you to the same output.
So now, if you have an output,
in order to determine which input generated,
you actually have an infinite number of inputs
that could have been mapped to that output.
So that's why it's computationally impossible
to actually find what input.
You might have a chance to find it,
but you'll have to iterate over all possible values,
and there's an infinite number of values
that could have a collision on the same output.
Okay, so secure hash functions have the same properties
with one additional property.
What we want with secure hash functions is we want a hash function
that if we apply it on two input data points,
and these data points only differ by one bit,
we want the output data to be very different.
That's the extra, let's say, property that secure hash functions have.
Okay, so this is expressed here by this first bullet point.
Any change from data to data star will lead to a completely different string
when you apply the hash function h over data star when compared to h over data.
Okay, otherwise, again, it receives as an input variable size.
It returns as an output fixed length, okay?
and then it still has that property that if we know the output and the hash function,
it's very hard to determine which input generated the hash function.
So using hash functions, we can now implement practical digital signatures
and this is what modern-day systems actually use.
So let's say again Alice wants to send a message to Bob.
We exchange the public keys, right?
And now Alice prepares a packet here,
prepares a packet that contains the message or the data that Alice wants to send to Bob,
the hash function that Alice wants to use, and of course the signature.
And the signature, we will calculate it as the hash function applied over the data.
And then we encrypt that result, that output, using Alice's secret key.
And then we encrypt this entire packet using Bob's public key, send the message to Bob.
Bob will be able to decrypt the packet using Bob's secret key.
Right?
Bob will be able to read the data,
will be able to read the hash function from the packet.
Right?
And then what Bob needs to do is he needs to decrypt the signature
using Alice's public key.
And then he needs to recalculate that hash output
by applying that hash function over the data.
And if those two results are the same,
it means that the message actually came from Alice.
So we have, again, practical digital signatures, right?
The hash function, the output of the hash function is smaller, right?
You can have hash functions that can return 256 bytes for kilobytes if you want, okay?
But it's way smaller than if you were to duplicate one gigabyte of data
to send some signatures, right?
So the overhead is way small.
So now to be able to send a gigabyte of data,
you send a gigabyte plus, let's say, four kilobytes of data for the hash output,
and then maybe some more bytes of data to encode hash function than we want to set.
Okay, so these are the two main mechanisms
to which security is implemented in distributed systems.
Okay, then of course high-level mechanisms like authentication, authorization, trust, right,
and these are implemented with a combination of different kinds of solutions.
But the most important, let's say, building blocks for security are encryption, decryption,
and, of course, secure hashing.
Okay.
All right.
So what I want to do, it's a 720.
Let's take a break.
All right.
So somebody asked a question.
So the hash function is sent by Alice with the packet.
Correct.
So the hash function gets sent with a packet.
Now, a lot of times the way actual applications work is that you have the
algorithms implemented both on Bob's and Alice's side.
So then when you send the hash function,
you just send the name of the hash function that you want to use,
and then the implementation already resides on both of their systems.
All right, perfect.
So let's take a quick break.
So it's 7.20.
All right, almost 7.20.
So let's come back in 15 minutes at 7.00.
That would be 35, I think.
So it's 7.35.
All right, we'll take a break, and then we'll come back.
talking about scalability in distributed systems.
I'm going to have one to do tomorrow.
Oh yeah!
I'm very soft, you know.
So I have to do stuff since COVID.
Okay.
So I'm kind of like, is it cool if I just...
I'll do the class and just learn on my own?
It's still doable, yeah.
So I would say just choose a programming language that you feel more comfortable with, you know?
And I can just send you some extra resources.
And you can just spend...
Yeah, just send me an email.
Well, it's going to be tomorrow anyway, so.
We don't need to know when, but yeah.
And these resources, I mean, you can probably go over them in like three hours in a weekend.
And then I think it will give you enough.
Because we're not really using like advanced things.
It's all on the internet.
It's all figured out.
Yeah.
Cool.
No problem, yeah.
Again, as long as you spend that time...
I've had students in the past in this situation as well and they didn't have a problem.
Okay.
In the end, it's how much work you want to put in here.
Yeah.
All I have is time of now.
You can ask me now, it doesn't matter.
Yeah.
The recording was what you said.
So I dunno, right now it's like I'm giving it harder.
So basically according to my knowledge, ahasian
Hashing serves on different purposes than encryption and decryption.
So I was able to understand how does it solve the problem of security.
Because for example basically hashing is serving to solve the problem of integrity.
Exactly yeah yeah yeah. So to make sure that if there's a file and we download that, there's a hash with that and we just get the confirmation that the file which we downloaded is the same which was uploaded. So in this way we know that this was the good file.
Yeah, that nobody tampered.
Yeah, nobody tampered.
But when we are talking about exchanging a message,
for example, I'm sending you a message,
then how does the hash solves the problem of encryption?
So it's not the problem of encrypting the message,
it's the problem of actually validating who sent the message.
So that would be authentication.
It would be authentication.
So how do I know?
Even if I encrypt something, right, if somehow, you know, let's say that you shared with your friend your public key, but I somehow stole the public key, right?
And then I sent you a message, right, and you're like, oh, I only share my public key with this person, but I sent you an encrypted message, so you think it came from your friend, but it actually came from me.
So the hashing, right, allow you to actually sign the messages so you can validate to see who sent the actual message.
So basically we are validating the signature?
Yes.
Oh, so it serves the purpose of the integrity of the signature.
Exactly, the integrity of the signature, yeah.
Now it makes sense.
Yes.
That's my kidding.
No, you don't have to be sorry.
Yeah.
I thought that we are talking about encryption.
No, no, no.
Yeah, because right, the hash functions, they don't do encryption, because there are only
one way.
Yeah.
You cannot decrypt from them.
And now I get them.
And a lot of it was just like using functions.
Are you coming from undergrad or industry?
No, I'm coming from industry.
All right.
Come back with a master's.
Sure.
What were you doing before?
I was the one who messaged about the server.
I'm trying to remember because I received a lot of messages.
What was it about the server?
Okay, okay guys so any you know again there is no restrictions in this class for programming assignment one
you can use any hypervisor you want. I think I'm going to install on both.
Yeah, why not? It depends from both of them.
I was planning to use remote access it anyway.
So that's the plan with that thing.
Here's an idea, if you want to be able to connect the machine without using some crazy firewall stuff to tailor the scale.
I'm gonna write it down here.
Okay well it doesn't usually go there.
Basically it allows you to create a VPN with your own purse.
It's free to use for a certain number of computers I think.
But basically it allows you to, again, set up a small VPN and it will allow you to connect from your system without doing any kind of crazy network setup.
Because what happens, right, if your server is at a point, you're probably behind some sort of NAT from your internet service provider.
So there's no guarantee that your internet service provider will give you a public IP.
It will be very hard for you to connect to the machine without doing any kind of service.
So they solve this problem.
You can just install it, set it up, register your machines, and then you can SSH between
them anywhere you want.
I just reached out to the systems guy.
Yeah, take a look at it.
I discovered this technology, I think, three years ago, and I was like, man, I wish that
I knew that.
I used to do all of those heavy configurations.
Yeah.
What do you call it?
A lot of times.
Oh, okay.
Oh.
I didn't mind .
I was from Chicago.
Yeah, from Chicago.
I'm from Seattle.
Oh nice.
It rains a lot.
Yeah.
It's not too bad.
I just I wish you would be a little bit colder.
Oh, yes.
I have to let I've studied on and all that stuff.
that hash tables are used to encrypt and decrypt passwords.
This is almost similar to that.
So again, write hashes can be implemented either in a secure way, for security reasons, or
for hash tables.
But I would say, so the hash tables, or dictionaries,
I would say that they are actually data structures that help you search for elements.
So these are search data structures because the list and the vectors of the linked list, right, they have very poor lookup time.
The hash tables and the binary trees.
That's exactly what I said, that they are used to just point to a certain specific location and then you can look up the whole user name and password and all that.
Exactly, exactly. So they can be used, for example, in an application
If you want to sort the credentials in an efficient way because you've got to search
to validate the credentials, you can use hash tables too.
And no hash tables, no hash locations can be same?
It's mostly on the eastern side.
Right, we don't want them to be the same, but sometimes you do have collisions.
So then the question is how hash tables solve collisions.
There are two ways.
So you have two kinds of hash tables.
You have open address and closed address.
Yeah.
So yeah, let me tell you.
Yeah, you'll get used to it. It's not too bad. You just dress in layers.
I used to live in Boston.
Oh, yeah. You'll be fine.
Think it's a little more now.
So if you go to ...
They have an entry in Wikipedia.
It's open-up dressing.
Closed.
Yeah, here it's like, in a couple hours, especially like the main streets around here.
They're cleared immediately.
It's funny because it's in Seattle.
Resolution is a little.
Oh, yeah.
KORI BORNAKA, MD, ANTHONY IS THE
chaining solution which I thought it was called node addressing. It's when you have a collision on the same
address, you create a link there. While with open address you move elements around.
Yeah sometimes, we don't get super around. So you reuse the address.
This is what we studied in systems. Yeah so anyways you would have studied these in the other
I've studied these in the other courses, but anyways, feel free to go over them again.
It's good to have a good understanding.
It's a beautiful city, a lot to do.
And you don't have to have a car here, which is really cool.
No, and especially with the red ones.
It's pretty convenient.
It was 24 hours.
It was just amazing.
I mean, you don't have that, everybody complains about it.
But, like, I used it to live in Boston for a little while.
The tea would take forever.
It tetrified.
It would be late and not show up sometimes.
This is great.
I got to rely on this.
Michael.
Kevin.
Pleasure.
Is this your first quarter, second quarter?
This is my fourth quarter.
Fourth quarter?
Masters, yeah.
Yeah, working through it.
Yeah.
Cool.
Like I said, I took undergrad here, so I was able to skip all the courses, which is really
nice.
Saves a lot of money.
Which is really, really convenient.
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah, it's like 10, 15% of the standards.
But actually you have to implement it.
Yeah, all that's up to that.
It's really expensive, and everything's not expensive.
I feel like it's better than-
Yeah, so we'll implement it as part of the application,
but once I understand the principle balancing
can come in different forms.
Again, we'll see.
So the main, if you were to abstract them,
made for you is either data partitioning,
or sometimes the balance is also part-partitioning.
So data partitioning versus partitioning.
And then how you partitioning these,
that's how you balance your load.
Balance it out of data, or by computation.
Yeah, I love public culture.
It's OK, we'll get to that point.
It was really cheap because I think it's
like moral to try it.
There should be housing.
You have culture here.
Food is good.
So like master or slave.
So no, those are actually full tolerance.
This will be more covered in distributed systems to class.
Because if I go back here, there is a bunch of chapters here.
So we're only going to cover in this class, architecture,
processes, communication, and coordination.
But fall tolerance has that, you know, master slave, you know, primary backup operations,
eventual consistency, that kind of stuff like that.
Yeah, absolutely.
Fresh water.
It's super important.
And the lakes and the beaches too, some people don't realize how much of a beach town it
is.
Yeah, security.
Yeah.
Someone is trying to use security.
I feel like they probably use more than the beaches.
Yeah, probably.
because we were able to separate it for like public use.
It's a component obviously.
Correct, correct.
So it's kind of like the misconception here, right?
Oh, you have to have a centralized solution.
Centralized solutions, they are not good.
They are good, especially if they are logically centralized and physically shouldn't.
But again, sometimes simpler solutions are better.
Manufacturing right on the lakeshore, so.
Can't really go in so far.
I'm from security, cyber security major, so that's why I was asking.
Yeah yeah yeah.
Because if we had to, let you mention the more difficult class problem is easier to
use.
I feel like I'll use this class to learn more about the security .
Correct.
And the more complex the system is, not just security, but also performance can decrease.
Openness can decrease, right?
it can be harder to maintain, hard to expand,
hard to interoperate with other systems,
distribution transfer as well.
So it affects everything.
So adding more computers is not always the best solution.
Twinos are also.
Yes.
Correct.
And we've got to solve those problems.
Yes.
I'm quite excited.
I don't know if they require it.
They require you to have to know it.
No, I don't think so.
Yeah, we'll see. So we'll spend most of the time looking at communication.
And low-level communication, right, but then we'll use high-level communication as well.
High-level has built-in features for security.
So you can do encryption information by default, which you want, right?
So when it comes to security, again, sending the data between computers, you want it to be secure.
You don't want it to send...
Nobody says that, that was maybe 40 years ago, when the Internet was free, and you're
sending passwords in plain text, but we don't do that anymore.
And then it depends on the application.
When you store passwords, for example, in a system, you never want to store the password
here.
A hash of the password.
You want to store the password inside.
If somebody breaks in, if it goes your hard drive, you know, physically that's here, they
never have access to the password.
Right, the hacker machine.
So you want to sort of hash it.
So again, some small principles apply.
It's very rare that you need to do something very sophisticated and unique.
So when you ask the question.
That's pretty strict.
That's okay.
I've had hackers to do like, dehash.
There's nothing like dehashing, but what they do is, when they have a password, they try
to hash different passwords and then when the hash matches they know that
brute force right yeah so actually it's very hard to attack the hashing
algorithms so they attack different so for example right so when you think
about security think it as concentric circles right and the circle in the
middle is typically the mathematical model usually very hard to attack and
And then we have the software implementation,
and then we have the hardware implementation,
and then we have the users that are using.
Usually, the users are the weakest link.
So when people attack the passwords,
they usually make assumptions.
Oh, people won't lose very long password.
They use words from the user client.
But in using that, you can reduce that search.
And then you can brute force it faster.
So that was one way that's the real value.
In the end, you have to brute force it in some way, unless you know weaknesses of the
mathematical algorithms.
So if you know weaknesses of the mathematical algorithms, then there are those.
Also, I was trying to search that what are...
They really don't care about the actual word.
was coming up, that modern quantum computer.
That's just Seattle.
It's a weird .
Yeah, so asymmetric encryption schema.
See, the asymmetric actually, they're harder to break.
Yeah, but the key exchange.
Don't be wrong.
There's a reason why I go to North America's or in Seattle.
It's the best weather in the country in my opinion.
There's no problem.
Yeah, yeah, I mean, yeah.
So you might want to read if you're very passionate about it.
Yeah, so he's the creator of SSH implementation, so for the client and the server.
So, he's a major contributor to OpenBSD, and OpenSSL.
So he's one of the main people.
So, he was a programmer for a long time...
He'd be like an hour outside in the policy, so he wrote some books as well.
Talks about security, talks about some of the pitfalls of today's security.
And hunting for the fact that there's no such thing as a completely secure system.
If you were to grab the computer, power it off, encase it in a concrete ball and throw
it in the ocean, it can still, there are still ways to break into it.
So there's no such thing as completely secure.
That's important to understand.
The strategies are not to try to make things perfectly secure, but detect when things don't
go down.
Sorry?
Detect when things, a hacker breaks into the system.
So that's also important as well.
Oh, very cool.
Monitoring and detection is as important as the security ...
Yeah.
Now that you rage ... anyway, send me an email or I can send you the name of that guy.
So he wrote a book on Daytime.
And he talks about it on security.
Have you heard of Chuck Norris?
He's kind of like a superhero in security, although he's considered.
But he's actually really good.
His observations are beautiful.
I will say it's right now.
Perfect.
Thank you so much.
Yes, of course.
I always recommend a group of California.
Everybody says, oh, what about California?
California is really expensive.
Yeah, it's too sunny.
You get nine months of clouds in Washington State.
But if you grew up with the clouds, then it's not a good person.
Yeah.
I would also like to go out.
There's the Orca Pods nearby.
This would be cool to see.
What?
Orca Pods.
Oh, yeah.
I think they go into the sound too.
They have those boats that go out and just look at the stuff.
They have a guaranteed picture of a worker or something.
I don't know if they actually do.
I don't know if they could guarantee it.
I'm sure there's a resident pod or something.
Yeah, a lot of wildlife.
That's the one thing about Chicago that I noticed.
There's not a lot of wildlife, it's really kind of...
Yeah, they're kind of busy.
You see deer every once in a while, it's harder up in uptown, sort of urban.
But there's also a huge coyote population.
Really?
They live in the parks and stuff.
Oh yeah?
Yeah, they just only come out at night, that's true.
These things are scary.
Yeah, they're not too bad, they kind of leave you garden.
They do cats, though, or something like that.
They do, yeah.
Unfortunate small dogs.
Yeah.
Yeah, we have a really healthy coyote population.
every once in a while you're catching them.
Uh-huh.
They sound crazy, doesn't it?
Yeah.
I think there's a pretty good population
along Linkin Park, around the lake.
Yeah.
Cool.
That park's massive.
It runs from just past north of you
to a little north of here, actually.
I feel like there's so much to see in Chicago
that you could spend your entire life and not see like that.
Absolutely.
Yeah, so much.
But it's an adventure.
Yeah.
So, you've got to see this adventure.
Yeah, it's better than just living in the same way.
I don't know, I have some friends who like, they grew up in a small town, they'd say
a small town, they look bad at the small town.
It's not bad life.
I mean, just like, you could do more.
You can see more stuff.
I mean, you could see more stuff.
Yeah.
It's an amazing city.
And I like that all the neighborhoods feel like little towns kind of have their personality.
It's very similar to like London or something.
Yeah.
As far as like, it's more like a village kind of thing, different villages.
Yeah, they all kind of like, condomerate into one big city.
That's the problem with Seattle, is they knock down...
I have a commercial real estate buddy of mine.
He said in the 90s, they made a deal where it's like, you can knock down, Amazon owns
75% of the physical city.
So they knocked down all the cultural, like, where neurona played and stuff.
Like this meant it looks really nice, but everything looks cement in class.
It's all the same now.
Yeah.
Versus here in Chicago you have like different architecture, depending on where you're at.
Yeah, absolutely.
Oh, that's one thing I would recommend.
You haven't done season might be coming close.
Checking out the architectural libertarian.
That's what people have said.
A lot of history.
Cool.
Yeah.
And to go to the city.
It's better than Boston, in my opinion.
In Boston, everybody's angry.
Everybody has a different opinion about the right way to do things.
And if you don't do it the right way, then you're wrong.
And they get angry.
Everybody has a different opinion about the right way to do it.
So no two people have the same idea.
Somebody's gonna get angry.
It's not a bad thing.
It's just like everybody's stressed out.
It's also very expensive.
It's the- like for housing is the highest in the country.
And you don't really get a lot of-
Do you not hear any of that at all?
Like 300,000 for like the shoebox that's falling apart of town.
That's too much.
Yeah.
And I hear the food's not as diverse I guess.
It's Italian and seafood, I feel like seafood.
I mean you can't get good seafood in Chicago I think.
Yeah.
They're by labor.
It's probably not as good as like in Seattle.
Yeah.
I guess in Seattle,
she's good with a very good.
Yeah.
And I don't see the point in eating Italian,
but you're looking at home,
I don't see the point in eating Italian.
Especially like Italian-American.
Yeah.
That's with Austin there.
All right, let's get back to distributive systems.
We'll see, maybe we can finish a little bit further.
But anyways, we talked about various goals.
The last goal that I want to cover is scale or scalability.
And a lot of the times, this is actually one of the main reasons
why people don't build distributive systems
is because they want to improve the performance of an application
or they want to be able to provide a service to a lot of people.
So, and to better understand this notion of scalability,
I think we have to understand a little bit the evolution of computers,
especially in the area of supercomputers.
Because distributive systems actually,
or result, a byproduct of a different approach
for building a supercomputer.
So again, I'll take you way back before I was born,
all right, 50, 60 years ago
when people were building computers, right,
all of the computers were single node,
single processor, single core, right,
one instruction at a time
and they were looking at how do we make things faster.
There were various techniques that they used.
They either made the clock of the computer faster,
So how many instructions per second are being executed by the processor?
They looked at various kinds of parallelism, including instruction parallelism.
And we'll see what this is later.
But the key aspect was that the computers were not connected over any network.
This came very late in the history of computers.
And the powerful computers were huge, were sometimes as big as this room.
They had a lot of redundancy built in and a lot of fast hardware.
They were very expensive.
So once people started developing network technology to connect our computers into a network, some people decided to explore to see what would happen if we were to, instead of buying a very expensive computer that costs tens of millions of dollars,
What if we were to buy a bunch of computers that cost less than a million dollars and then just interconnect them over a network and then program the application in a way where it uses all of these compute nodes.
And that was the first, let's say, computer cluster that was built.
And it proved that you can actually build computers that can run fast while also maintaining, let's say, a low budget.
Right. And they built it using commodity hardware.
So they built it using desktop computers that you can go and buy off the shelf.
They just interconnected them and implemented, again, the applications in a way where they knew how to use these resources.
So that's where, again, the notion of distributed system came to be, so to these parallel computers.
And what people started asking themselves very early on is, okay, if we add more computers, does the performance of the system increase?
Now, the way you can think about this performance, let's say that I have a scientific application where I process one terabyte of data.
We'll start small scale, although modern applications, they usually process terabytes of data.
So let's say I have a terabyte of data that I need to process.
And I have on a computer, I can process that data at one gigabyte per second due to the nature of the computation that I'm doing with that computer.
So this means that if I run the application on one single computer,
it will take me 1,000 seconds to process the data.
One terabyte is 1,000 gigabytes, one gigabyte per second means that it will take 1,000 seconds.
Give or take.
So if I can add another computer to the mix and if I can split my data,
let's say equally between the two computers,
this should allow me to then process the data faster.
So if I use both computers at the same time, each computer will process 500 gigabytes of data.
That's still at one gigabyte per second.
It means that now I can process a lot of data in 500 seconds, again, give or take.
And I can keep on adding computers.
I can keep on adding cores, maybe on my processors, or increase the speed of the processors to try to reduce this execution time.
but one thing that we usually
do not take into consideration by default
when we think about splitting the application in this way
is that we assume that there's not going to be any communication
between the computers and that's still the difference
between a modern day mainframe and then a cluster of computers
right so in a mainframe the communication
between the different cores right
can happen at very fast speeds or very low latencies
But between computers that are now connected over cables in different racks, for example,
it takes a little bit longer to transfer the data.
We're limited by the laws of physics, in addition to the overhead of sending the data from one computer to the other.
So, a lot of the times when we want to split an application across multiple computers,
we forget to take into account that there's also an additional overhead that gets added,
which is the overhead of transferring data between the computers.
and we want to transfer data for various reasons.
The main reason is if the algorithm requires us
to synchronize the state between the machines.
So sometimes an application can be penalized in a way
where minimal communication,
and those are called embarrassingly parallel applications,
those scale very well.
But there's a class of applications
that actually require a lot of communication.
For example, artificial intelligence
requires a lot of communication.
Even if you were to train a larger model across multiple computers,
you need to synchronize that model at various stages of training
so then there's a lot of communication that happens between the computers.
And if you remember, from the memory hierarchy pyramid,
the network speed, or network devices,
actually sat at the bottom of the hierarchy.
So they were the slowest in terms of performance.
So even though you add more machines,
your performance will increase up until a point
where you have so many machines that you have to coordinate between them so much
that you're spending most of the time communicating over the network
rather than being processed.
So the performance can decrease.
So when people talk about increasing the scalability of a distributed system,
it refers to how do we analyze how many compute nodes we can add
before performance goes down
and what kind of modifications do we have to do inside the algorithms to make them work well with multiple machines.
So when it comes to the different areas or types of distributed systems,
we'll talk about supercomputers as well very soon.
I would say 99% of supercomputers nowadays are actually built as clusters of computers.
So there's no one single mainframe.
There's no one single supercomputer.
99% of supercomputers in this world are built by connecting to very high-speed interconnects, brick-level algorithms, tens of thousands of server machines.
So those servers are connected to high-speed. They have usually special cooling and special operating systems that they use to run and special programming languages and compilers.
But this is how modern-day supercomputers are built.
So, in order to run a very large application, people thought about how do we add multiple computers to increase the scalability of the system.
And I know I mentioned, so we want to increase the scalability out of two reasons.
So, in the world of supercomputers, we typically have one application that we want to run very fast.
while in the world of let's say enterprise systems
corporations and banks and stuff
what we care is how many services we can provide per second
how many requests we can provide a second
think about a bank that wants to allow people to pay everything using their credit cards
so the credit cards every single time you use it
they have to send a request to the bank
so the question is how many requests per second can the bank process
to be able to satisfy as many clients as possible.
So again, this is that area where we want to provide a service
to an increasing number of users.
However, when we talk about scalability,
a lot of the times people focus on what we call size scalability.
So this refers again to how do we increase the number of processing resources
or the number of users in the system, or how do we make an application run faster.
However, there are also two other different kinds of scalability that are also very important
and sometimes we don't take it into account.
So one of them is geographical scalability, which refers to what happens with the system
when we increase the distance between the components of the system.
and then administrative scalability,
which refers to what happens when our distributed system
spans across different administrative domains.
We'll explain what these mean.
For size scalability, usually the reason why we want to add more computers
or more processing power or more resources
is because we reach some sort of limitation in our system.
So, this goes back to what we talked a little bit earlier about what a computer is.
So, some limitations might have to do with limitations by the CPU.
A processor can execute a certain number of instructions per second.
Let's say you can overclock the processor, but it has a hard limit of how many calculations it can do.
So, in order to be able to do more calculations, to process a larger application,
or to provide services to multiple users, you just need more computational power.
It gets more CPUs to do those computations.
Other times, the limitations could be
either memory or storage capacity.
So your applications are large enough
that you need a lot of RAM
or you need a lot of storage to store them.
This is very typical, for example,
for database applications.
So the Amazon store,
they have a lot of products,
a lot of users,
so they need to store all of that information
in an efficient way
so that if somebody searches for something,
and they can get the results of those products pretty fast.
So one of their bottlenecks in their system
is probably going to be storage and memory.
Now, there are other distributed systems
that rely more on sending data over the network.
So maybe network bandwidth could become a limitation as well.
So the solution would be to increase
either the number of network cables that connect,
the number of fiber optics,
or to upgrade copper to fiber and so on and so forth.
Now, when it comes to geographical scalability,
this is where some assumptions that we hold
when we build distributed systems,
if they are, for example, in a local area network
versus a wide area network,
it might lead to different kinds of behavior inside the system.
so typically when we think about a cluster of computers
we think about a tightly coupled cluster of computers
so it means that the machines they usually reside in the same room
and they're connected to some sort of you know wired connection
you know and there is some sort of symmetry there
in how the connection is implemented right
so there are some guarantees in when you send data over the network
where you will receive it in a certain month of time
But, for example, when you go to a wider network, let's say now that you have to distribute your system across the Internet, right, you have a few machines here, a few machines in New York, a few machines in Los Angeles, right?
So once you distribute them this way, you're going to encounter, of course, different kinds of latency expectations.
Latency means how fast you can send data from one computer to the other, right?
Even if, for example, we were to implement a perfect software algorithm that sends the data at the speed of how fast the electron moves through the wires, right?
The longer the wires, the more it takes time for the electron to actually move.
So we're bounded at some point even by the laws of physics.
Even for fiber optics, we're bounded by how fast the photon goes through the fiber optic to send data.
So there are, of course, limitations.
There are, we will see, types of applications, and the most popular types of applications are synchronous client-server applications, where basically you have a client application that requests a service from a server and just basically waits for the server to reply.
The longer the distances, the slower the application will be.
So these are things that we simply are very hard to, again, to overcome.
And the solution would be to actually deploy more hardware closer to where the resources are needed.
Just to give another example for geographical scalability,
when Netflix started building their streaming services,
they had to think about, okay, we can build, of course, the software to do the streaming and everything,
but the question is, how do we locate data closer to where it's needed?
So they had to think about,
how do we build data centers across the world,
initially across the country, then across the world,
so that whenever there's a very popular movie
that is in high demand in a certain region,
we need that movie into those data centers
so that it's closer to where it's needed.
Because if we had only one data center
and everyone wanted to watch their movie from that same data center,
we're just limited by the network bandwidth.
We just cannot.
We have a certain level of, I don't know, terabytes per second that we can send, but
we cannot go over that limit.
So the only way would be to distribute or decentralize the system and move stuff around
so that we can satisfy those requirements.
When it comes to wide-area networks, so when we're connecting our distributed systems across
the internet, sometimes the links or the connections between the machines becomes
unreliable. So when you have a cluster of computers in the same room,
you have copper cables, you have a certain guarantee that the only messages
that are being sent are from the computers inside the room. But when you send data
over the internet, we're not sending over one single copper wire.
So, for example, when I'm contacting youtube.com from my phone,
I'm sending data over the wireless network. If there are other
computers that connect to the same wireless access point, there could be interference
so my performance could be slow.
But let's say that it's not, right?
So it sends the data to a router, a wireless router.
Then the router is probably connected to some sort of wire cable to another router, right?
And then that router is connected to other routers and so on and so forth
until it reaches, you know, maybe to fiber optics, it reaches my destination.
But, for example, if I were to send data over the Internet,
if, for example, the router that is supposed to forward my packet
from one network to another dies, right?
I have to resend the data.
So that creates, again, a certain kind of uncertainty when it comes to sending data,
which means that now when you program the applications,
you have to program in a way where they can withstand that kind of data loss, let's say.
That's why, for example, when it comes to streaming video,
they have various kinds of solutions there.
So when, for example, YouTube streams videos,
they will send you the frames of the videos in a compressed form, and your program will decompress it.
But if, for example, certain frames get lost, they don't get to be sent.
Actually, they use the algorithms on the client side in your browser to actually try to interpolate the missing frames.
So they try to predict what were the missing frames.
That's why sometimes you might see like a blurry thing.
Sometimes you see a little bit of lag there.
So you see some inconsistencies.
But those are bearable enough.
People won't really be that bothered by them unless they're like fanatics about,
oh, I want to have the most clear image always.
But usually it's not the case.
But anyways, but it depends on the application.
For example, if you play a video game and you're playing a multiplayer game
and you're part of an esports competition, then latency is very important.
If you lose a frame, you're going to get a lag.
Your character will be shot or destroyed or whatever.
so you lose the game.
So that's an example where things are very important.
You don't want to lose data that well.
That's why usually when they do esports tournaments,
they do them in a confined area.
They don't do them across the internet.
They bring everyone to a location.
They connect to dedicated cables,
and they create a local area network
that has more predictable performance.
All right.
And then the last point when it comes to geographical scalability
is the lack of multipoint communication,
and this has more to do with the way the protocols
over the internet are implemented.
We'll talk more about it.
But basically, multi-point communication means multicast,
where multicast means when you want, for example,
to send a message to a subset of machines from your network.
This can be implemented in local area networks,
but it's typically very hard to implement
over the wide area networks
because you do not have control over the routers
that are set up over the Internet.
Actually, what I wanted to do is
I wanted to also ask you a question
because I'm talking about the Internet
and I'm talking about networks.
for again, students that have heard about it, you know, what is the difference between
internet and intranet? Because I know it's kind of the difference between
local internet network and wider network. But in terms of the definitions of these
terms, you know, what is the difference between internet and intranet?
Internet is in between one single corporation and internet is all over the world.
true true so that's one way what about so what are the components of the
internet and the components of internet so those are the type of networks right
but the components you know what's what's connected inside an intranet and
what's connected the side and in time so intranet right you have a network of
devices. It can be, you know, you can have sub-networks as well, right? But an
internet is a network of networks, right? So the way the internet works is you have
multiple internet service providers that connect their own networks between each
other and then allow people to connect their computers or their internets to
them and then that's how we build the internet. Okay, so inside an internet you
can have this multi-point communication because you control the devices by the
Once you go across the internet, you're going to use somebody else's network,
so you don't have control over it,
so it's very hard to then implement this multipoint communication
without using maybe overlay software.
Okay, so you don't have built-in solutions.
And some other limitations when you go geographically distributed,
it also makes it very hard to identify resources.
This is called naming in distributed systems,
so how do you name the resources,
how do I identify them in an inefficient way?
We'll see these.
We'll talk about some strategies that can be used to identify.
Okay, now for administrative scalability.
So this has to do with when you need to now scale your distributed system
and it spans various administrative domains.
So this means it spans various organizations or institutions
or countries that have various policies.
So, to give an example, let's say that you're Mark Zuckerberg, right, you're creating Facebook, this social network, you're revolutionizing, you know, the way people talk over the internet.
And, right, one of the challenges, how do you build this to be efficient?
How do you build this to scale in terms of size, right, the number of computers, the connections, right, so that everyone can talk in real time with each other?
or not in real time because
it's asynchronous, you're sending a message
and the person can receive
it, there's a little bit of a delay
not a problem
but one of the challenges that they
had to face that is not
discussed, it was more of a
policy slash technical
challenge, so when they built
this application, they knew
that they had users, they had to log in and
whatever, but what happens if for example you
want to run Facebook in a country
that says only
people that are 18 or old can use Facebook.
Otherwise, you should deny them access to the platform versus a country that doesn't have
that limitation versus a country that says, okay, you're allowed to
publish this kind of information, but you're not allowed to publish political
information. So then how do you implement this platform
to support these different kinds of policies? So this is what
it means when we talk about administrative scalability. It means how do we build
a distributed system that can be tuned, that can work in different ways depending on the
different policies that it spans.
So, this is a challenge not only for enterprise systems like Google, Gmail, Google Docs and
their communication services and Facebook and Twitter and all of these, but this can
also, for example, appear as challenges even in the world of supercomputers.
So what happened is that 30 years ago, as the United States was funding a lot of the
national labs in the U.S. to build supercomputers, usually the supercomputers are hosted by the
national lab.
And each national lab has their own policies, has their own users, and has their own ways
of storing the data on the computers,
processing the data on the computers,
so on and so forth.
So as they were building
these independent supercomputers
that were competing with each other,
at some point,
the United States came and said,
hey, what if I want to run
a very large application,
let's say for the Department of Defense,
and I want to use
all of the supercomputers,
not just one.
This is what they wanted to do
during COVID.
I want to process
the genome of the virus.
So I want to be able to use all of the computers,
all of the supercomputers.
And they hit a hard limitation.
They hit a hard limitation because, again,
different supercomputers have different policies,
different rules on how the data was accessed
and who's allowed to access,
what kind of computation you want to run.
So they had to figure out solutions
on how to run an application
across multiple supercomputers.
So this gave birth to the notion
of computational grids.
So the grid is the solution that they came up with,
which is basically a set of applications
that virtualize the notion of computation in data.
And then by using this notion of virtualization,
they can then apply, they can implement it
on various computers with various kinds of policies.
Anyway, a lot of details, not really that important.
Now, what I want to say is that there also exists a class of distributed applications that are actually immune to the challenges of administrative scalability.
And usually the applications that fall into the area of peer-to-peer, let's say, distributed systems or peer-to-peer networks,
they don't have to implement various kinds of policies for different kinds of reasons,
because what they do is they push the responsibility of implementing the policies
to the actual peers or the clients themselves.
So they don't have to be implemented as part of the, let's say, network or the distributed system itself.
And the best example for this is, of course, the BitTorrent protocol.
I'm not sure if I'm too old at this point, and I'm the only one who knows about BitTorrent,
but I have a feeling that you've heard about it as well,
which is this protocol that can be used to share data.
That's what I'm going to call it.
Now, of course, the data that you share depends on the user.
So the policy of what kind of data you want to transfer falls on the user,
not on the system itself.
The system is just meant to share data in a very efficient way.
And there are, of course, there's a reason why they built the BitTorrent
and it was a problem that they were trying to solve.
And we have a dedicated set of slides for looking at the BitTorrent protocol
that we will look at later.
But just as a little preview, they were trying to solve the problem of transferring data from a personal computer to another personal computer in a very efficient way.
The internet is built in an asymmetric way.
So us, the regular users, we are considered consumers.
While the people with data centers and servers, they are considered producers.
So when you buy Internet from an Internet Service Provider, they will give you a download speed and then an upload speed.
Usually, the upload speed is less than a download speed.
So you can download at 100 megabits per second, 200 megabits per second, but usually you can only upload for like 10, 20 megabits per second.
And it's because, again, when they design the Internet the first time, they design it in this producer-consumer way.
where the servers, they can push more data
and as the consumers, we can download more data.
But now, what if you want to transfer data
between your friends?
You're limited by that upload speed.
So this is where BitTorrent came in
and they designed this clever protocol
where they can create multiple replicas of your data
and it allows you to download different chunks of your data
from different sources simultaneously.
Each source gets uploaded from the computer
at a small speed, but you can download at a fast speed.
So that was the main reason behind it.
Now, the fact that we used it to transfer various other kinds of data,
that's a different story.
But again, the BitTorrent system itself is not responsible
with implementing any kind of policy.
That's all shifted towards the users.
That's why the creators of the BitTorrent protocol,
they cannot be held liable if people use it to transfer data illegally.
It's actually the people themselves that are actually transferring
the data online.
So this applies also to other systems as well.
The earlier versions of Skype were also implemented as a peer-to-peer system,
but then once they got bought by Microsoft, it became a relay base,
so they lost that, let's say, capability.
And then Spotify as well can be peer-assisted.
So for example, if you have multiple devices,
they can assist each other actually by transferring if they have the same melody.
Windows also has this as well when it does updates, right,
He can detect if there's another computer in the same network that has the same updates,
he can transfer the updates from that computer.
Okay.
Now, when it comes to scalability, usually people focus on size scalability the most.
This is the main challenge that they're trying to solve.
Geographic scalability and administrative scalability becomes relevant once you reach very high scales.
So typically, company level scale, like large companies.
So for us, what's more important is to understand, you know,
how do we scale and distribute systems in terms of the size of the system?
So we can, let's say, process an application faster or provide a service to multiple users.
So there are three kinds of techniques that can be used to actually increase the size scalability of the system.
One of them is to hide communication latencies.
And this is something that we will see a little bit later when we will talk about communication.
So, for example, applications could use asynchronous communication.
So, asynchronous communication means that if I need some sort of service,
I will send a request to the server and then I will wait until the server sends me back the reply.
Asynchronous means that I can send a request and then do some other useful computation
while I wait for the server to send me the reply.
We will see, for example, web browsers actually implement asynchronous communication.
It can, of course, have separate handlers for incoming responses.
We will see that this can be implemented by using multiple threads and multiple cores
that are available in your systems.
The only issue is that, when it comes to hiding communication latency,
is that not every application fits the model.
Sometimes, the application might not have other computation to do,
and it just has to wait for the data to come from this way.
But this is one way that you can use to improve, let's say, the performance of applications.
Another technique is you can move computation to the client, for example.
This is a very popular technique that is used in web applications.
So the first diagram here on the top shows the way web applications were built 20 years ago.
So let's say, for example, the web application had a form where the user had to punch in some data, right,
and the data had to be validated.
Usually, the validation would happen on the server side, right?
So, the user would type in the information, the information would be sent from the client
to the server, the server will validate if it's incorrect, you let the client know, they
type in the data again, and then this back and forth messaging happens between them until
the form is correct.
But, this is inefficient because you're sending a lot of data back and forth, right?
What you want, you would like to be able to send a request in one go that is validated
and correct.
So, this is only validating the structure of the form, not the data itself.
For that one, you still need the server's input.
So, in the second diagram, this is what modern-day applications do, is they actually ship,
they send part of the code from the server to your browser, to the client, right?
And they can do that validation directly on your machine before they send the message to the server.
That way, the bandwidth, right, is, you know, more clear, right?
You don't have that much data being transferred, which means you can now add more clients simultaneously
to send and receive these requests.
So this is another technique that can be used
to increase the scale of distributed systems.
And then the most popular way to increase,
let's say, the size, scalability of your system
is to partition data and computation
across multiple machines.
So you can move both data and computation
or separately depending on the situation.
We will see in programming assignment 3, you will actually need to accelerate parts of your application.
And the way you do that is by actually partitioning your data and the computation that happens with the data across multiple cores on your system.
so you can move computation for example from servers to clients or from various peers
you can use decentralized maintenance services so you partition the data across multiple computers
you can decentralize your information system so that there's no one centralized entity that
I could track everything.
I can just go from one server to the other.
For example, the internet was built by following the hyperning data structure
or the hyperning structure for organizing information.
So when we talk about how do we organize information on the computer,
the most common way to organize data in a computer,
mostly related to secondary storage, is the file system hierarchy.
So you organize the data in the form of files and folders.
right then you can have folders inside folders and files inside folders and
this is one way to organize the data however over the internet we organize
the data using the hyperlink structure so this means that we have web pages and
web pages can point to other web pages so I can have a link to another web page
so this is a decentralized way of organizing the data because you're
going to have to have a root of your hierarchy right each web page can reside
independently and can connect to other web pages independent.
Alright another technique that is also popular when it comes to increasing the scale of
distributed systems is replication and caching.
So you make copies of the data available at different machines or level of the machines.
So there is a difference actually between replication and caching.
I know we sometimes maybe use it interchangeably, right, in day-to-day language, right, in day-to-day communication, but they actually mean different things.
So usually replication happens on the server side while caching happens on the clients.
So, again, when it comes to web applications, replication is heavily used.
So actually the internet, whenever we are accessing a website for example, there is a very high chance that we are actually accessing a replica of the website and not the actual server.
So the internet servers providers implement content distribution networks, which is a specialized distributed system that actually brings data closer to where the people are to where it's needed.
Yes?
Can I add a word over there?
What is the difference between like cache and cookies?
Cache and cookies.
So cookies, they only store a specific kind of data while the cache...
That's a good question.
I think the difference is, again, more in terms of the purpose of it.
So you're using the cookies to store some sort of session information so that you don't have to re-log in
or re-authenticate every single time.
While with caching, you're storing data that you're accessing often.
So they're both kind of like a caching mechanism, but one is used for authentication while the
other one is used for content.
Alright so again, file servers and databases can be replicated, websites can be mirrored,
of course modern day web browsers, they store caches of course including on your phone as
well and that's why when you're accessing websites that don't change too often
they load very fast because the webpage is already stored on your web browser.
And then of course when you're transferring large amounts of data in the
form of files, file caching is also another very popular solution but we'll
see more, we'll talk in more detail about these techniques later. I just wanted to
highlight them here. And of course so certain techniques that can be used to
increase the size scalability even though it allows you to have multiple computers there
maybe achieve redundancy they can also harm performance sometimes so for example with
replication the main issue is that if you need to keep all of the replicas always synchronized
right you can add extra overhead inside your system so as an example let's say that again
I'm Google and I have Google Drive and I allow multiple people to access a Google Doc at
the same time and modify.
But let's say that the people, they actually reside at very large distances, right?
So, and I have, right, the document, I want it to be replicated so that it's closer to
the users.
But now the problem is I have to keep all of those documents synchronized.
So, right.
So when I send a request to modify something in a document, I got to make sure that I modify
all of the replicas before the other users see it so that everything is consistent.
So this introduces extra messages that you have to send.
So now instead of just sending one message to one server, you're sending multiple messages
to multiple servers.
So keeping the data consistent, you know, usually adds some sort of overhead, which
actually sometimes harms performance and scalability.
Now if there are applications that can tolerate inconsistencies
then the problem can be avoided
you don't get drawbacks
but it depends on the application
Okay
Alright, so then
the last thing that I want to do as part of the introduction
is I want to talk about
a classification of distributed systems
so we finished talking about
the design goals
again, keep in mind design goals
sharing of resources, distribution transparency, openness, dependability, security, and scalability.
These are the main general goals that people follow when they build distributed systems.
And then there are, of course, other sub-goals and objectives that we follow.
So now what I want to do is I want to talk a little bit about an attempt to classify distributed systems
into different kinds of distributed systems.
And then after we're done with that, we'll talk about some of the pitfalls of distributive systems.
And then we'll be able to move to architectures, finally.
So I'm just going to brush over this pretty fast.
You'll be able to find more details in the book.
It's very hard to classify distributive systems just because there are many properties that different kinds of distributive systems have in common.
We'll see at the end, when we look at hybrid, you know, double calls and distributed systems is basically a combination of various kinds of distributed systems.
But the most important part, and again, from a historical point of view, distributed systems, let's say, became a thing because of the attempt to build faster computers.
And the techniques that they used to build faster computers,
the early techniques actually were looking at how do we parallelize various aspects of the computer.
The earliest form of parallelization refers to instruction parallelism.
So, you know, if we have a program, right, and parts of the program can be executed,
let's say, you know, independently from other programs,
the questions can be executed as part simultaneously.
So that's one form of instruction level parallelism.
There's also, for example, if we're processing a vector of data and we're doing an addition element by element, why can we design computer systems that can actually do an addition on four elements at a time to increase the performance of the application?
So this led to various kinds of designs of processors.
And this led actually to an attempt to create a supercomputer that actually used multiple processors.
So it is very common nowadays when you go to a data center and when you look at a server, the server will have a motherboard and typically have not just one processor, but you will have maybe two or four processors connected on one motherboard.
So that's one way to increase performance by adding more processors so you can compute more things in Petro.
This technique evolved into the notion of multi-core
but we'll spend more time in the processes chapter
to understand what a core is
and what's the difference between a core and a processor
but for now just think about these multiple cores
as being multiple processors
Now what was very interesting about these multi-processor
and multi-core system
is that they were connected inside a computer
in which all of the processors had access to the entire memory space of that computer.
And this was achieved through some sort of interconnect.
So you'd have the processors themselves,
some sort of common interconnect that allowed all of the processors to access all of the memory.
So this is called a shared memory system.
So the shared memory system means that all of the cores of the processors
can access the memory.
Now, there are two kinds of shared memory systems.
You have uniform memory access systems and non-uniform memory access systems.
So UMA and NUMA.
Uniform memory access systems are a type of systems in which all of the processors inside that system
can access any byte of memory from any memory module at the exact same speed.
non-uniform memory systems,
they have the property that
a processor
will be able to access
a certain memory region
at a certain speed,
sometimes faster if it's closer,
and then will be able to access
the memory of another memory region
at a lower speed because it's farther away.
Or because the interconnectors
not implement an all-to-all communication between the processors and the memory so this is something
that we don't really encounter that often when we buy regular computers however there was one chip
that actually had non-uniform memory access so most processors that we buy nowadays they come
configured with uniform memory access so all of the cores inside your processor will be able to
access the memory of your system at the same speed. However, when AMD released the first and
second generation Threadreadweaver processor, right, it was the first processor, they had a lot of cores,
right, 32, 64 cores, right, it was very large. Now, the way that they built this processor is
actually by combining together multiple smaller processors. So this meant that the first and the
second generation processors, it means that they implemented non-uniform memory access. So the chip
itself had, let's say, eight channels to connect to memory DIMMs, to memory chips. But the way it
was organized is that you had four different, let's say, zones in your processor, and each zone
connected directly to two of those channels. And then the connection to the rest of the channels
was done through a lower speed interpreter.
So this means now that even though you had 64 cores in one processor,
it meant that 16 cores were able to access a quarter of your memory very fast,
but the remaining three quarters very low.
So now the challenge was when you wrote that program,
you had to write it in a way where there was minimal communication
between these different NUMA regions
if you wanted to get the best performance.
Otherwise, you would see performance degradation.
Now, after they perfected their technology, starting with the third generation Threadripper,
they were able to make it uniform memory access.
However, in the BIOS, you can go and change it, and you can still enable, if you want,
non-uniform memory access, which allow it to get even higher performance.
Okay.
So, anyway, these are, again, the shared memory systems.
There are, of course, a few advantages when using shared memory systems, right?
You can write one single program.
They can run on all of these processors.
We'll see very soon in the third chapter, we'll talk about threads.
It's a mechanism that you can use.
And again, if you want to access any region of memory,
you just pass the address of that memory that you want to access.
But again, these systems became very expensive to build.
The most important component here in shared memory systems
is actually the interconnect between the processors and the memory.
You might have heard a few years ago, maybe two years ago,
again, if you watch tech news and stuff,
you might have heard some controversies regarding the Intel,
I think 13 and maybe 14 generation processors that were starting to fail.
So people were complaining that they were getting blue skin of death on the system.
They were not working very well.
and what was happening actually with those chips is that they were overclocked so the again the
system was meant to was it was tuned to you know run very high speeds which generate a lot of heat
and the heat ended up actually damaging the interconnect between the cores and the various
other components which then damaged the chip and you're not able to use it. So again the interconnect
is very important usually dictates the price of the processor so the higher
speed the interconnect usually the more expensive the prices but people also
looked at you know how do we build computers differently in a way where it's
cheaper but maybe we can still get very good performance so they also started
building private memory systems or those computer classes that I mentioned so in
In a private memory system, we still have a bunch of processors, but each processor is connected to its own memory module,
and then we usually either connect the processor or we connect the machine in which the processor is running
to some sort of interconnect to other machines that have their own independent processors.
So in a private memory system, the processor only has access to its own local memory,
but it does not have access to the memory of the other processors.
So if we want to transfer data, for example, between two processors, what we have to do is we have to copy that data to the interconnect, send it to the other processor, store it somewhere locally, and then we can process it.
So modern-day supercomputers, they use a combination of private and shared memory architectures.
So usually on a single node, on a single server, they use a shared memory architecture, but then across multiple computers, they use a private memory architecture.
Okay.
So, again, some observation.
So, multiprocessor and multi-core applications, they're typically easier to program because you just have to write a program.
You don't have to implement any kind of mechanisms in your program where you have to transfer data from one memory to another.
You just access the various, you know, memory regions that you have on your computer.
people have tried over the years
to implement some sort of virtual shared memory
for private memory systems
however these are very difficult to implement
and very difficult to implement in an efficient way
because the virtual memory techniques
have a very hard time predicting what the user wants to do
or what are the next instructions
Usually, the programmers of these supercomputers or distributive systems,
they know the application very well.
They know the data movement very well,
and they can make certain decisions that a general virtual memory cannot.
So that's why even though people have tried to implement them in practice,
people, when they program these supercomputers,
they use specialized programming languages in which they explicitly say
which data has to be transferred at which moment of time.
So having control over that allows you to actually get the best performance.
So when it comes to cluster computing, most supercomputers out there, they usually follow this architecture.
The cluster of computers, they're typically implemented as a group of high-end computing systems connected to some sort of high-speed interconnect.
Some properties of computer clusters is that the cluster is homogeneous.
So it means that usually the compute nodes that are part of the cluster, they are the same.
This makes it different from an enterprise system.
So in an enterprise system, you might have different servers with different architecture,
different amount of RAM, connected with different kinds of speeds that get added together,
that get expanded over time.
So the data center gets expanded over time.
But when people build a supercomputer, they typically build it with the same kind of compute nodes connected in a symmetric, let's say, network.
So homogeneous also means that they're running the same operating system.
And again, they have almost identical hardware.
And then they might or might not have managing nodes.
So these managing nodes are a little bit of interesting history.
Modern-rate supercomputers, they do have managing nodes, but they play a different role.
but I kind of want to say 20 years ago,
there was a supercomputer built at Argon
called the IBM BlueGene,
which was very interesting.
So the compute nodes
actually did not have any logic
that helped them to load an operating system.
So the compute nodes
were very simple computational,
let's say, chips
that you had to load the program into them
and then you would already know
how to execute one program.
So technically,
there was no operating system at all.
So they only knew how to run one single program.
So that supercomputer had a bunch of management nodes that ran typical, let's say, computer architectures, like the x86 architecture.
And those management nodes would actually load the parallel supercomputer program on all of the chips in parallel.
And then it would start all of them simultaneously to run the application.
Once the application was done, the chip would shut down.
So anyways, very extreme ways of running computers.
We don't do that.
You're not going to turn the computer only to run one program and then shut it off.
You run multiple things, you know, they usually happen.
But certain supercomputers were designed in this way.
And then the last aspect is that usually in supercomputers,
they tend to decouple the various components of a computer.
So we talked at the beginning about the processor, memory, and the network and disk.
In a supercomputer, they tend to separate these
and put computation memory in one type of compute node,
put storage in another kind of compute node,
and then they use this high-speed interconnect
to actually transfer data from the storage to the compute nodes
whenever they have to do computation.
All right.
And then, of course, we talked about grid computing as well,
which is, again, this attempt to connect multiple supercomputers
from various organizations.
We're not really going to spend a lot of time.
Okay.
All right.
So, again, one class of distributed systems is this class of petro computers
or classes of computers, supercomputers, you can call them.
Okay.
They were designed and they worked in a specific way.
Now, distributed systems have also been adopted by the enterprise world.
So this is by corporations.
Right.
So back in the day, they used to have a lot of humans that do accounting and keep track of various transactions.
But once computers became accessible, they started adopting this technology to automate their process.
So we can store spreadsheets nowadays, databases with information, transactions.
They can all happen inside computers.
And in the early days, when they built these computers, they were built in a way where they were not networked.
So the computers were separated.
There were different organizations.
and at some point it became very beneficial
to actually maybe connect these computers
in a network and have them communicate
with each other.
So in the world of
enterprise systems, this
problem of how do you connect them
and how do you make the applications work well
is called a problem
of integrating applications.
Sometimes the applications were
from the same organization, but sometimes the applications
were from different organizations.
Just to give an example, let's say
that you have a company like United that manages flights,
another company like Hilton Hotels that manages hotels bookings,
and then another company, let's say Hertz, that manages car rentals.
And all of a sudden comes, let's say, Expedia or Priceline
that decides that, hey, I want to build a system
that actually allows users to book a flight and a hotel and a car
all in one single interface.
from all of these different users.
So now, all of a sudden, I have to figure out
how do I combine the data from all of these databases
and how do I create operations over this data
that is consistent with all of these databases.
So people have to think about,
okay, how do we combine these enterprise applications?
So this is the enterprise application integration,
let's say, problem.
Some of the earlier techniques that they used
were tied to the fact that a lot of the applications in the enterprise world are designed around
databases.
So when you go to a corporation, they usually use databases to manage transactions, to manage
operations, to manage accounts.
So this is all done using databases.
So this actually gave the people who were designing the systems the opportunity to actually
using some existing solutions.
So if, for example, I'm Priceline and I want to build this bigger application,
what I can do is I can use the notion of nested transactions.
So if somebody comes to Priceline and they want to book a hotel and an airplane,
I can create a bigger transaction made out of smaller transactions,
and then I can deploy these transactions independently.
And only if these two transactions complete successfully,
then the entire transaction completes successfully.
Otherwise, I need to roll back.
So to implement this, people created a type of distributed system called the Transaction Processing Monitor, the TP Monitor.
So this was, again, a generalized solution that allowed people to connect multiple database applications
and allowed client applications to send one big request, right, to break it down into small requests
that can be processed independently by various servers.
and only if all of the sub requests were completed successfully,
the entire BN was completed successfully as well.
Right?
Because you don't want, when you go to Priceline,
to get hotel, car, and airplane ticket, right?
But then one of them fails.
Right?
You want all three of them to succeed in one transaction when you buy it.
All right.
So, again, this was one of the earlier solutions, let's say,
to how do we integrate applications.
But there also came the question, you know,
because they were tied to the databases,
what if two applications wanted to communicate
between each other directly?
Right?
So maybe, you know,
less expensive to create a database transaction
just to implement a very simple communication
between applications.
So then they had to figure out
what are the other ways
that we can implement communication
between various kinds of applications.
So in the world of,
let's say, enterprise systems,
There were two kinds of communication technologies that were developed.
One of them is called Remote Procedure Call, which we will study in depth in this class,
and the other one is Message Oriented Middleware, which we'll also study in depth in this class.
These are two ways that you can implement communication,
and they can simplify the process of integrating applications.
Both Remote Procedure Call and Message Oriented Middleware are implemented at the middleware level.
If you remember when we talked in the lecture recording, we talked about distribution transparency and how it can be implemented using this middleware layer.
Inside the middleware, we can also implement communication between applications.
And we will see that there are various kinds of communication styles that can be implemented.
Okay.
Now, when it comes to integrating applications, if I were to ask you, hey, you have two programs running on the same computer, right?
And I want you to implement communication between them.
The easiest thing that you can do is you can create a common file between those two programs.
One program can write to the file and the other program can read from that file.
Boom, you have communication.
It's not the most efficient, but it works.
And it was one of the earlier techniques that people used in the enterprise world.
Shared databases is another way to implement communication.
And then more effective ways are, of course, remote procedure call and messaging.
In remote procedure call, what the systems do
is they allow you to actually call a function or a procedure on a different server.
And it uses the exact same semantics that you would use when you write a program.
So it makes it very easy for you to implement that communication.
You will see in this course, as part of designing your, let's say, client-server application,
I will ask you to use various kinds of communication technologies.
We will start with a low level, which will be very hard because we have to do a lot of operations to make communication work.
But then, we'll get a chance to implement the exact same application by using the remote procedure call, which will simplify things.
We'll basically be able to write a program that basically calls functions from an object that resides on a different computer.
And all of this, you know, communication is implemented by the remote procedure call middleware that you will need to start as part of that application.
you will see it will simplify things and the messaging allows you to actually
implement various kinds of messaging styles so synchronous asynchronous
persistent transient we'll see what the differences between them are basically
allows you to decouple time in space when we send messages around and these are
also very popular ways of sending data not just only in enterprise systems
nowadays but also inside cloud systems as well
yes into another computer machine basically when we are sending one
executing a command it is a remote procedure call, can it be called an
example of RPC? No no so ssh does not use remote procedure call to implement
that communication. In that ssh we are also executing... yeah you can run commands
I know you can run commands and applications, but the way the underlying implementation of SSH is actually using messages.
It does not use remote procedures.
So when you use SSH, you don't call a function from another program.
You can call programs.
You can transfer data as well.
But it uses stream communication.
It doesn't use, you're not calling a function.
It's not discrete anymore.
We'll see.
I think anyways
the things that I mentioned, they will make more
sense once we actually look at remote procedure
call because we will need to define a little bit
what remote procedure call is and how it
works and I think that might help you give
loads a better understanding.
There's also, when it comes to communication
again there are different flavors
so once we understand those flavors
as well we're able to actually understand the
differences between SSH and RPC.
Okay
for now just trust
me they're different.
Okay. All right. So again, in terms of classifying distributed systems, we have, of course, the federal computer systems or supercomputers. Then we have the enterprise systems. And then lastly, the ones that are very popular right now, which if you've heard of Internet of Things or IoT, the distributed pervasive systems.
So this is the next generation of distributed systems in which the compute nodes are small, mobile, and they often embed in other larger systems.
And they usually have, they can be classified in some subcategories.
So ubiquitous computing systems are pervasive and continuously present.
So when people think about building a smart house, that is full of sensors that detects when you wake up, it cooks a toast for you, it makes coffee as well.
It tells you, it reads your last email, it turns on the car as well.
If it's wintertime, all automatically, just by looking at what you're doing right now.
All right, so again, this is an example of when you beat with us, you know, distributed pervasive system, right that it's everywhere, but it's also always also continuously present.
So you're always interacting.
Mobile computing systems, right, also became very popular, especially with self-driving cars or the robots, you know, the carrier right now, you know, different kind of products, you know, drones as well, you know, that can fly by themselves.
Right.
So these are going to systems that are mobile.
They move around and they have their own unique challenges.
For example, if you want to send an update to a Tesla car,
you need to identify where is the Tesla car and you need to find the best path.
And if the car is actually moving while transferring the data,
you have to predict where to send data to the next access point.
So each of these types of systems, they have their own, let's say, challenges when you have to implement.
And then sensor networks, of course, are also very important as well.
People want to build smart cities as well where you have many sensors that collect data.
we will see there are various kinds of challenges when you collect that data,
you know, how do you process it efficiently,
and people have been thinking about, you know,
various ways to implement generalized frameworks
for all of these three subtypes of pervasive systems.
But I'm not going to spend too much time on them.
You'll be able to find a little bit more information in the book.
They're not going to be in the quizzes.
They are, although, a hot topic,
so you might want to maybe invest a little bit more effort
because people are trying to build various kinds of frameworks
to deploy these pervasive systems.
A type of framework that is very popular right now
is the edge computing system, right,
which is kind of a response to building these small sensor devices
or mobile devices that are using cloud services.
So, for example, the reason why we can use Google Translate
very efficiently, for example, on our phones or Google Lens
to translate images as well in real time
is because the applications
don't actually connect to the cloud.
But this creates a problem
because you have many small devices
and they're all trying to connect to the cloud
to do various kinds of processing.
This will start
saturating the network bandwidth.
There's so much network that we have so far
to connect all of these devices.
So then people start to think about
how do we build frameworks
that can build some sort of computing system
between the sensors
of the mobile devices and in the cloud servers.
And we can do some local processing.
So this is, again, the notion of edge computing systems.
But how do we, you know, how do we place these nodes?
You know, let me see.
There was a few.
I think I might have removed those slides.
But anyways, there are a lot of questions here that are not answered.
And how do we do this efficiently and effectively?
How do we organize the information systems?
We don't know yet.
So this is a hot topic where people are trying to figure out various kinds of solutions.
In terms of sensor networks, I was mentioning, you know, how do we run queries over the data?
Right.
Again, if you connect many sensors and they're all broadcasting data all the time,
why would we need very high bandwidth networks to be able to capture the data, which we don't have right now?
So what people are looking at is how do we do some computations on the sensors?
And maybe we can put a little bit of storage on the sensors to store some sort of data for a while
and then have the sensor maybe calculate an aggregate of the data.
But how do we program this in an efficient way that's an open question still.
All right.
So the last thing that I wanted to mention have more to do with the pitfalls in distributive systems.
So these are, let's say, concepts or topics that we usually don't think about.
So whenever we implement an application that is locally on our computer, right,
We don't have to think about, for example, the latency between transferring data from one program to the other.
Inside our local computer, the latency is very low.
We can usually transfer data at milliseconds level.
Once we go across a geographically distributed system, it can take us seconds now to transfer a piece of data.
So you have to factor that now inside of the application.
a lot of times we assume
that for example the network
especially in an local area network
we assume that the network is reliable
secure, homogeneous
but once we go in the wide area
network range we don't know
because we don't know exactly what path
or packet will take throughout the internet
we don't know exactly which route
it will go through
and over the internet there's no guarantee
of reliability, you have to build
of course security, there's no guarantee
that the internet service provider will encrypt the data for you.
And then the network is not homogeneous.
We also sometimes assume when we implement smaller applications
that the topology doesn't change.
But across the internet, it can change,
especially if you involve also mobile devices,
then they move around.
So even the physical topology changes.
We sometimes, like I said, assume latency is zero, right?
So latency increases with distance.
We also maybe assume that the bandwidth is infinite
or that the transfer cost is zero.
This is another aspect that, for example,
Facebook had to take into account
was that I wanted to deploy this application
in different countries
that had different bandwidth capabilities.
So how do I design a system that works well
on one side, it might be slower,
but on the other hand, it's fast.
So they had to take that into consideration.
And the last aspect,
sometimes we assume
when we think about a distributed system,
there's going to be only one administrator.
But that's not the case, especially if you build multiple data centers across the world.
You have to have multiple administrators doing various kinds of operations inside the system.
But as you will be working on the programming assignments for this class,
you'll encounter some of these pitfalls.
And in the end, the best way to learn it is by actually learning it through practice,
learning by coding and then realizing, you know, in a sense, the assumptions that you made
and then correcting those assumptions and then correcting your style of program.
Okay.
So that's all that I wanted to cover when it comes to the introduction.
I can take a few more questions before the class ends.
I usually leave 10 minutes.
If you want to take the quiz in class, you can do that.
But if you want to leave it for later on, that's fine as well.
The quiz, it doesn't matter in which section you are.
We'll take it on D2L.
So on your laptop, my recommendation, read the chapters.
and then take that with, again, open book, open internet.
And my recommendation is pay attention to them
because they're a good way to prepare for the exam.
There's no midterm in this class.
So that's one of the ways you can prepare for the exam.
The other way is in the last two weeks,
I'll release an exam study guide,
which contains a big list of questions,
but without the answers.
So questions that have been asked in the past in the exams.
The exam is open book, open notes.
So it can also bring handwritten notes
or printed notes.
I don't know what I'm trying to write.
Yes?
Do you have to write code in the exam?
No, but you'll need to write either pseudocode
or diagrams or use natural language
to explain how you designed parts of the programming assignments.
So that's the only section that you'll need to
either write pseudocode or diagrams.
Mostly the exam is antiquist.
I'm so sorry, say it again.
The exam is what?
Mostly the exam is MC-based.
So MC means multiple choice?
Oh, I see.
So there will be, I think, three long answer questions, three medium answer questions,
and then I think 28 short or multiple choice questions.
So the short and multiple, short questions means you have to write one or two sentences.
Multiple choice, only one answer is correct.
And then again, three medium means you need to write a small paragraph,
and then for the long answer, you need to do the diagrams and other stuff.
It will be two hours or one hour?
So I think the exam is two hours.
Yeah.
So the exam is two hours.
However, my recommendation is that you go over the exam study guide.
So in those last two weeks, I know you might be busy with other assignments,
but try to allocate some time to go over the questions.
You can, again, talk with each other, of course,
to try to figure out the answers.
You can swarm intelligence.
That's great.
But make sure you go over those questions.
Usually, students that use the exam study guide,
they usually actually do very well in the exam,
and they finish before the two-hour mark.
Students who encounter those concepts for the first time
and they have to search it through the book and through the slides,
they usually don't finish online.
So that's why my recommendation is, again, do the quizzes, go over the chapters.
And when you prepare for the exam, once you go over the questions, you'll see that you
remember a lot of the answers.
Okay.
Yes.
And no midterm?
No midterm.
No.
You'll have a lot of work on the programming assignment.
Yes.
How did this work for the class?
Oh, thank you for reminding me.
I keep forgetting about it.
So I don't keep track of attendance.
However, for the first two weeks, I need to submit a report to the university.
So on D2L, there is a survey.
So if you go on D2L, more, and then on your surveys,
or even if you go here on the introduction and programming assignment one,
I think there should be an introduction attendance survey.
Please make sure you fill this out by Tuesday next week
so that I can keep track of attendance.
I can send that report to the university.
but otherwise I don't keep track of attendance
so it's up to you
again
if you come to class it gives you the opportunity
to ask more questions
the first couple
of lectures were more theory intensive
but when we go to programming assignment 2
I'm going to focus on
the practical aspects as well
we'll look at code as well in the various
programming languages
a combination of theory
and also practice as well
so anyways
I don't keep track of attendance, but for students that are active, I'm going to try to remember your names, okay?
And I usually give extra points at the end.
And then for students that are in the Flex section, again, if you cannot make it in person, you know,
I usually give extra points for students who answer questions on the discussion forum on B2L.
Okay, all right, very good.
If there are no other questions, we can end the lecture here, okay?
Is there a way to connect, so we can use an IDE on our guest machine, the host on the
...
Yes.
You can start looking at on your own.
There's a lot of tutorials nowadays on the internet.
I'm going to show you after programming assignment how to do it with ES code.
Okay.
the modern-day ID's. If you use the jet brains one, eclipse whatever you want,
they don't have to support for remote development.
Over SSH. We use the exact same thing that you're using to connect and you used to connect to that remote.
So then if you wanted to use an IDE on our main machine, now we need to create a new public private key to connect to...
No. No. Use the exact same public private key. The exact same connection.
Is there any particular one that you prefer or we can use?
Anything you want.
I don't have any preference.
Well, I have preference for my own, but you guys can use that.
I'm not trying to tie you with it.
My recommendation is that I explore to see which one you're going to like.
Hi.
They are recorded automatically, yes.
So they are recorded, so they should be posted on D2L.
If you look here, if you go to the course home, they should be posted here.
Now here I have both lectures because I have two classes, but if I filter on in the CS45,
you see this is from last time, but last time I made my own recording, but otherwise they
get posted that automatic.
OK, so one other question.
For the GitLab and all the code that we have to do, do I need to be on the Fireboard to
do that or no?
No, no, no, no, you can do it from home.
Yeah, yeah, that's why they have that proxy thing the Bastion so that you know you can do it from home from wherever you are.
Okay, perfect. Thank you so much.
Thank you, have a good night.
All the best, good luck.
I also sent an email about the CXD.
Oh yes, I did receive it. I remember. No, I know because once I sent an email about the server,
I remember who you were. So you will get the more time on the exam and also on the quizzes. I already set it up.
Yeah, apparently now I'm having difficulty sitting for so long.
No need to explain.
So thank you for going to the, you know, the center, you know.
So the student center, you know, and I already received that information.
And like I said, even when you go and take the quiz one,
you'll have more than 10 minutes.
So it's 15 minutes.
Thank you.
So the same for the exam as well.
Okay, okay.
Thank you so much.
Are you in the in-person section or flex?
I'm in flex.
But I prefer taking in person. I understand more that way.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, that's fine. So for the exam, you need to register for the proctor exam.
So you know that.
Can I take in person?
Yeah, you can come.
I don't know. I would probably prefer to take it in the center. They give that option.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. So I can just stand.
If you go and take it with them, just let them know that, hey, I have extra time.
Okay. So they will give you three hours.
I don't know. Just having difficulty sitting.
Yeah, no worries. I understand.
thank you so much
all the best
good luck
have a good night
you too
You
Thank you.
.
We'll be right back.
Thank you.
You